<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between a minister and his parishioner concerning the Lord's Supper ... to which are annexed three several discourses, of love to God, to our neighbour, and to our very enemies / by J. Lambe ...</title>
            <author>Lambe, John, 1648 or 9-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12571400</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12571400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48477)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 322:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between a minister and his parishioner concerning the Lord's Supper ... to which are annexed three several discourses, of love to God, to our neighbour, and to our very enemies / by J. Lambe ...</title>
                  <author>Lambe, John, 1648 or 9-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 179, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>A Dialogue <hi>concerning</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Supper.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN A Miniſter AND HIS PARISHIONER, Concerning the <hi>LORD'S S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Principally deſigned for the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that never yet Received.</p>
            <p>To which are annexed Three ſeveral Diſcourſes, <hi>Of Love to God, to our Neighbour,</hi> and <hi>to our very Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. LAMBE,</hi> Rector of <hi>Wheatham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhop's Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:2"/>
            <head>
               <list>
                  <item>To the Right Worſhipful
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sir</hi> John Garrard <hi>Kt. &amp;. Bt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sir</hi> John Witteronge <hi>Kt. &amp;. Bt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>To the Worſhipful,
<list>
                        <item>James Witteronge <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Godman Jenkins <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Edmund Smith <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Rich. Emerton <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Godman Jenkins <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Valen. Laurence <hi>Gent.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COnſidering our frequent Exhortations to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to come to the Holy Sacrament, the many Motives, and thoſe eſpecially from the benefits
<pb facs="tcp:63466:3"/>we receive thereby, ſo often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated and preſs'd upon them; and above all, conſidering the example of You that are the chief and leading Men, whoſe Wiſdom they juſtly value, and have recourſe to in moſt of their Affairs: it cannot but ſeem exceeding ſtrange, that our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions are ſo very thin. If we, at any time, deſire them to give us a reaſon of their abſence, they either decline the queſtion; or, if we preſs it, they ſtop our mouth by ſaying they are not ſit, and who will perſwade them <hi>to eat and drink their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation?</hi> And thus they ſatisfie themſelves with that excuſe which is indeed an aggravation of their fault. The very truth is this,
<pb facs="tcp:63466:3"/>to the looſer ſort, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as all Religion, is a thing indifferent, that I do not ſay, deſpiſed; to many of thoſe who are well inclined, (by reaſon of their crude and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted notion of it) it ſeems a tremendous dreadful duty that they are afraid to aſſiſt in; and to others a myſtery that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible: and thus the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt reſtraint of impiety, the ſtrongeſt bond of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Love to God and man, is deplorably neglected, to the prejudice of Chriſtianity, and the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Holineſs. Wherefore to reform this grievous evil amongſt us, (ſince the efficacy of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Country Pariſhes, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hindred, by reaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:63466:4"/>inconſtancy of our hearers, through the extremity of Weather, and other cauſes; and ſince ſuch an effectual inſtruction of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that are ſcattered in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable diſtances, and are continually employed in their affairs, is impracticable) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved with my ſelf to digeſt the Nature, the Ends, the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and preparation to the Holy Sacrament in as eaſie a method, as familiar a Style, and as ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my Preaching as I could; that all pretences of ignorance, fear, or unfitneſs, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd for the time to come. And I humbly beg of you to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the deſign, and joyn your influence upon the People, with my endeavours, that God may
<pb facs="tcp:63466:4"/>be glorified, his Worſhip fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, and our Souls, and the Souls of thoſe that are under our care, that have any relation to us, or dependance upon us, may be ſaved: which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prayer and endeavour of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sirs, Your faithful Paſtor, and affectionate humble Servant, J. Lambe.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March 28. 1690.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:5"/>
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Z. Iſham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mar. 13. 1689/90.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63466:5"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE Between a <hi>MINISTER</hi> And His PARISHIONER, Concerning the HOLY SACRAMENT.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
               <p>SIR, a good morning to you, I come to give you notice of a Chriſtning to morrow at the Church, between eleven and twelve a Clock, if you pleaſe to be at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>It is very well, you ſhall be ſure to find me ready, by God's aſſiſtance, to do mine office: and I pray preſent my ſervice to my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63466:6"/>and tell him I commend his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, Zeal and Obedience in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Child to Church; and I hope the benefit and decency thereof will invite the reſt of my Neighbours to follow his example. But, I pray, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him to keep his time, and get his Goſſips in a readineſs, that neither the Congregation, nor the Child may be detained.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſh.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, Sir, yes, as for that matter, the Goſſips are beſpoke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; and for want of a better, I have promiſed to ſtand for one my ſelf, and the reſt are at hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis very well, but I muſt tell you one thing, the Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns that no man ſtand as Godfather to a Child before he has received the Sacrament: and I am aſhamed to tell you, you never received it of me, and I am afraid you never received it at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſh.</speaker>
               <p>Truly; Sir, if that be the Law, my Neighbour muſt look him another Goſſip; for it is a folly to lie, I never did receive. I never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63466:6"/>what it was you did, nor why you did it, nor what I ſhould get by communicating with you. I have heard your ſelf, and many others preach upon it very learnedly, as far as I know; ſometimes exhorting us to come, ſometimes preſſing us to a careful preparation of our ſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we preſume to receive, leſt the Sacrament ſhould do us more hurt than good; ſometimes upon one point, ſometimes upon another that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it: but my memory is very ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; indeed I cannot well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a Sermon, and I remember it worſe; but if I perfectly apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the meaning of the duty, no man ſhould be more conſtant at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than my ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I profeſs I am heartily ſorry, as well for your Ignorance as neglect. But I am glad however, that you are willing to be informed; and if you think good to accept of my ſervice, I will do the beſt I can to enlighten your mind, and aſſiſt your prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63466:7"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pariſh.</speaker>
               <p>Ah, with all mine heart, but I ſhall never underſtand you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you give me leave to propoſe ſuch Queſtions to you, as ariſe out of mine own mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Do ſo, ask me what you will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>If you pleaſe, then I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with what I ſee, and ſo proceed to enquire into the deſign and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. I obſerve then, that on <hi>Eaſter</hi> Day, and at other particular times in the Year, the Communion Table is cover'd with a linnen cloth, and furniſhed with a Patten of Bread, and Flaggons of Wine; I pray, Sir, what becomes of it, what does the Miniſter do with it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>After the Service and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon are ended in the Church, the Miniſter goes up to the Communion-Table, and after a ſerious confeſſion of ſins, and ſeveral Prayers and Thankſgivings, together with the Charity of the Communicants, for the moſt part, firſt collected and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up to God, and after a form of bleſſing or conſecration of the Bread
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63466:7"/>and Wine, he deals to every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant a morſel of that Bread to eat; and then he delivers the Cup into their hands, that every one may drink a little of the Wine that is in it, as you may more particularly inform your ſelf, by reading the publick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the Communion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, this may eaſily be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, I believe as much; but I pray, Sir, give me leave to ask you, what the Deſign, the Intention and End of all this is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Ah, that indeed is the thing which is chiefly to be regarded. For you muſt not think that this is done for the ſake of the Bread, the Wine, or the Company, as an ordinary friendly Compotation; but it is an act of Religion, which we are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to celebrate in Obedience to our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> who has made and ordained this breaking of Bread, and drinking of Wine together,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S</hi> Mat. 26. <hi>S.</hi> Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> the moſt ſolemn Ordinance of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Worſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63466:8"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>To eat and to drink together, the moſt ſolemn Ordinance of the Chriſtian Worſhip! how ſhould that be? ſurely there muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing farther in it, that does not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the eye, there muſt be a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Religious action, that I at preſent do not apprehend, but am very deſirous to be inſtructed in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt certainly there is: for you know it is commonly called the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and the principal reaſon of that,
<note place="margin">Catech.</note> (as our Church hath taught us) is this, becauſe the outward ſign, that is to ſay, the whole action that is done before our eyes, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command of God, preſerves in memory, repreſents and ſignifies ſome other thing that is inviſible, ſome Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical paſſage of former times, ſome duty thereupon to be performed, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeveral advantages we ſhall certainly receive thereby, which are aſſured unto us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd upon us, by the will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God, in the due Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration and uſe thereof: and thus a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63466:8"/>Sacrament is diſtinguiſhed from a bare religious Ceremony of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance or inſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech you Sir, be more particular.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I am very glad of your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Briefly then, our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our (as you may read in the 22. of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> at the 19th. Verſe) as He was eating the Paſſover with his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, immediately before He was betrayed, ſet forth and repreſented to them His enſuing death upon the Croſs, by breaking of Bread, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing the ſame unto them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Take, eat, this is my body which is given for you:</hi> and by taking the Cup (full of Wine) and giving that alſo to them, ſaying, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood;</hi> or as Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> recites it,
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my blood of the New Teſtament which is ſhed for you and for many for the remiſſion of ſins:</hi> and at the ſame time commanded them, by the ſame moſt proper and natural ſigns of bleſſing and breaking of Bread, pouring out of Wine, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63466:9"/>eating and drinking the ſame toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to continue a freſh remembrance of <hi>Him,</hi> and more particularly of His death, to the end of the World. <hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi> v. 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Thus far I hope I underſtand you, the Death and Paſſion of our Bleſſed Saviour is that in eſpecial manner which the outward Signs commemorate, exhibit, and refer to. But you ſaid that this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was more than a Religious Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of <hi>Remembrance:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray inform me in the full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and farther ſignification of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It is very well remembred; and if you obſerve the words of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, which I but now recited, you will eaſily perceive that our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour appointed theſe Sacred Signs not only for a perpetual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of His Death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but alſo of the ends and reaſon of it, as His Death was the Seal or ratification of the New Teſtament, or Covenant of Grace, which God has entred into with Man, conſiſting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63466:9"/>principally in this, that our ſins ſhall be forgiven, and our Souls ſhall be ſaved, through the ſatisfaction which our Saviour has made to God for us, if we on our part, believe His Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, rely upon His merits, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our lives. For ſo ſays our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Take, eat, This is my Body,</hi> there He appoints the Commemoration of His death. <hi>Given for you,</hi> there is the end and reaſon of it, <hi>which is given for you;</hi> Now, once for all, in ſubſtance and reality, and hereafter, to the end of the World, in the ſign and figure, as often as you celebrate the Myſtery. And again, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my Blood:</hi> the Covenant of Grace between God and us, which was ſealed and ratified in the Death of our Saviour, is revived, renewed, and confirmed to every particular Perſon, in this his Holy Sacrament, that receives it as he ought to do. You are therefore to underſtand the Sacrament, as a diſplay of the whole Religion of Chriſtianity; God on his part ſigning and ſealing his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63466:10"/>of Pardon and Peace to us, and we on the other part, covenanting with God to perform the Conditions required of us, with all poſſible exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the time to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive then that the Holy Sacrament is a Remembrance of the Sufferings of our Bleſſed Saviour, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the deſign and intention thereof, the Remiſſion of our ſins. That it is a confirmation of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace on the part of God, that He will be reconciled unto us through the blood of his Son, which is therefore called the <hi>blood of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> and on our part, it is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Faith in the Mediation of Chriſt, and a ſolemn obligation of our ſelves to perform the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required of us. Now, I pray, Sir, give me leave to ask you, what thoſe benefits and Graces are, which you ſaid were aſſured unto us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us in the due Celebration of this Holy Sacrament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>You may eaſily find out that your ſelf, if you conſider what has
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63466:10"/>been ſaid already concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Sacrament, and the end of its Inſtitution. Is it underſtood as the Seal and Confirmation of the Covenant of Grace? Why then the benefits we receive thereby are no leſs than all the bleſſings and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that Covenant, which is ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly confirmed, and aſſured unto us: Namely, the pardon of our ſins, upon Repentance, Grace and ſtrength to perſevere in a courſe of new Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and Eternal Glory in the life to come. This <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> this Covenant of Grace, is ſealed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to every particular Perſon in the Holy Sacrament: all ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons preſent, as believe the Goſpel of our Saviour, rely upon his Merits, and Repent of their ſins, are, at that very inſtant pardoned, if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere: So ſure as they eat that Bread, and drink that Wine in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our Saviour's death, ſo ſure ſhall they partake of His <hi>Body and Blood,</hi> that is, of all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which were purchaſed for us by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63466:11"/>His Death and Paſſion: and this is grounded upon the words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Take, eat, This: i. e.</hi> this Bread, which you are about to eat, <hi>is my Body which is given for you;</hi> and <hi>This Cup, i. e.</hi> this Wine in the Cup which you are about to drink, <hi>is my Blood of the New Teſtament.</hi> They ſhall not only be the ſigns of your Redemption by my Death; but they ſhall be the thing it ſelf; they ſhall be <hi>my Body and Blood:</hi> that is to ſay, the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and end of my ſufferings, pardon of ſins, and Eternal life, are aſſured unto, and actually veſted in all thoſe, who worthily receive theſe outward ſigns. <hi>For the Cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16. <hi>Is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt?</hi> Not only a Remembrance of his Body broken, but a Communion or a participation of the Body: by which, according to the faireſt and moſt natural conſtruction of the words, we can underſtand no leſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63466:11"/>than this, that as we bodily and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally partake of the Bread and Wine, which are the ſigns and repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of His Body that was broken, and His Blood that was ſhed for us; ſo Morally and Spiritually we ſhall alſo partake of the benefits, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and end of breaking his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſhedding <hi>His</hi> Blood, the Pardon of our ſins, and the Salvation of our Souls, if we receive the ſame with ſuch affections, and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mind, as we ought to do: and this our Church has taught us in her moſt Excellent and Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Catechiſm, <hi>That the Body and Blood of Christ are verily and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed taken and received, by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the Lord's Supper.</hi> By theſe Viſible ſigns, as by the Rod in your Copy-hold Courts, you have Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Seiſin given you, of all the bleſſings purchaſed for you by the Body and Blood of Chriſt, under the Conditions of Fealty to the Lord, and the Cuſtoms, Rents, and Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Mannor.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63466:12"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks it is not ſo difficult to underſtand the nature of this Holy Sacrament, and the reaſon of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution as I thought it was; I am heartily troubled that I have ſo long neglected it: I am convinced what an enemy I have been to my ſelf, and am now reſolved that I will never miſs an opportunity of Receiving.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>But hold a little! You had beſt conſider what you ſay, and what has been ſaid to you. For as the moſt nouriſhing of meats, received into a ſick and crazy ſtomach; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that wholſome juice, that ſtrength and ſpirit which it contains in it ſelf, and would certainly yield and give out to the body, does now but feed the diſeaſes of it, and fill it fuller of evil humours; not for want of vertue in the food, but for want of proper diſpoſitions in the Recipient. So alſo the Holy Euchariſt, though it contains, and is ready to confer, thoſe benefits and Graces I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed you of; yet you muſt not think that it operates as a charm, by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63466:12"/>the repetition of certain words, or the punctual celebration of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, (as you have already been inſtructed) but in a way that is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Rational, that is to ſay, upon this Condition, that the mind of the Receiver be duly qualified and prepared. There is therefore more imployed in this ſo ſolemn a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our Saviour's Death and Paſſion, than it may be you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of. It will not be the Body and Blood of Chriſt to every one that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Elements of Bread and Wine, which are the ſigns thereof, but only to ſuch as are <hi>duly qualified and prepared</hi> to receive them. God is ready to perform his part of the Covenant, if we have fulfilled, or are reſolved to fulfil, the conditions which are required of us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech you let me under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the utmoſt of my Duty, that I may prepare my ſelf as I ought to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſo; and becauſe the juſt and neceſſary preparation to any action whatſoever, depends upon,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63466:13"/>and is meaſured by the nature, the end, and deſign of the Action it ſelf; therefore I ſhall only trouble you with ſuch preparatory exerciſes, as you your ſelf ſhall acknowledge to be fairly inferr'd from the nature of the Holy Sacrament, as I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained it to you.</p>
               <p>Firſt then,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Is the Communion a <hi>Sacrament?</hi> does the outward action repreſent and ſignifie the whole tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of our Redemption. Begun in the Birth, continued in the Life and Preaching of our Saviour, and finiſhed in his Death upon the Croſs? Then a Religious Commemoration hereof, implyes, and ſuppoſes a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient explicit knowledge of that, which we ſo ſolemnly Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; becauſe the Knowledge of the Fact goes before the Remembrance or recollection of it, in the nature of the thing. It is neceſſary therefore, that you acquaint your ſelf diſtinctly with the Hiſtory of our Saviour's Life and Death, contained eſpecially
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63466:13"/>in the four Evangeliſts, before you can be qualified to receive.</p>
               <p>Again,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Do we underſtand the Holy Sacrament, not only as a bare external Ceremony of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, but as a confirmation of the Covenant of Grace, as the Seal of that Covenant, and all the Bleſſings of it to every Communicant that is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to accept the terms:
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.26.</note> 
                  <hi>This</hi> (Bread) <hi>is my body,</hi> and <hi>This</hi> (Cup) <hi>is my blood of the New Teſtament which is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> or according to S. <hi>Luke,
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.19.</note> This Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood:</hi> or as S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>a Communion of the body and blood of the Lord?</hi> then this implyes a competent knowledge, at leaſt, of the grounds and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Faith. And therefore it is abſolutely neceſſary that every Communicant be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed:</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the miſerable condition of all mankind, as well by reaſon of the corruption of our nature, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our many actual and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63466:14"/>tranſgreſſions, which expoſe us to the Anger and Juſtice of God, and to thoſe grievous puniſhments, annexed to his Laws, which we are neither able to undergo nor avoid.</p>
               <p>And Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the nature and conditions of our Saviour's Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between God and us,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10.</note> who, <hi>by the will of God has ſanctified us,</hi> who has put us into a capacity of Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Pardon, Mercy, and Eternal Life, <hi>by the offering up of his Body once for all,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note> who knew no ſin himſelf, but was made ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God through him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.26. 1 Pet. 3.18.</note> Who therefore <hi>took our nature upon him,</hi> that he might be capable of <hi>bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſins in his own body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, who by his death and ſufferings, according to the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Council of God, to us unknown, has offered ſuch a ſatisfaction to God, as with ſafety to the honour of his Laws, and the Juſtice of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he has been pleaſed to accept of; and has thereupon abundantly aſſured us of his readineſs to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63466:14"/>to us. So that if any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence continue ſtill between us, the reaſon thereof ſhall be wholly on our part.
<note place="margin">Col. 1.21. 2 Cor. 5.18.</note> 
                  <hi>For all things are of God who hath reconciled us to himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> That he hath now reſtored us all to a capacity of favour, Pardon and eternal Happineſs, upon condition, that we believe and hope in his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, through the merits of his Son; Repent of all our paſt tranſgreſſions, and ſincerely endeavour to govern our lives by the Laws of his Goſpel for the time to come. That inſtead of a perfect and exact obedience, (which the beſt of us are not able to perform) the purity of our hearts, and the ſincerity of our intentions ſhall be now accepted; and all our manifold tranſgreſſions, through hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane frailty, ſhall be now forgiven; through the ſatisfaction and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of our Bleſſed Saviour. <hi>That if we ſin,</hi> as we all do, and repent and amend, as we all ſhould do;
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>we have an Advocate with the Father Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, and He is the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63466:15"/>propitiation for our ſins.</hi> We have one that will plead our cauſe, and urge a Right that repenting Sinners have to Pardon,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> becauſe, <hi>by being made a curſe, he has delivered us from the curſe,</hi> that is, from the puniſhment of the Law;
<note place="margin">Heb 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and is able to ſave to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, all that come unto God by him,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing He <hi>ever liveth to make interceſſion for us.</hi> And that all this bleſſed My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of our Redemption, through the Croſs of Chriſt, is both ſignified and confirmed unto us in the Holy Sacrament. <hi>This is my Body which is given for you. This Cup is the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my blood.</hi> And therefore you cannot be qualified to receive, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you underſtand theſe Principles of the Chriſtian Faith. You cannot be qualified to enter into Covenant with God, till you underſtand the contents and articles of the Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Again,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Is the Sacrament a Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of your Chriſtianity? Do you by partaking of the viſible ſigns of our Saviour's death, by aſſiſting in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63466:15"/>ſolemn Ordinance of diſtinction, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and own your ſelf to be his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.18, 19, 20, 21, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>(as thoſe who ate things offered to Idols, were underſtood to conſent with the Sacrifices, to own and profeſs the heathen gods and worſhip?)</hi> Does God by his Miniſter offer and confirm his Covenant of Pardon to us in the blood of Chriſt, and are we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to conſent with all our hearts, to accept the Conditions with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and gratitude, to enter into Coveant with God our ſelves, that we will perform the Conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us? Then you cannot be worthy to receive, unleſs you ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe his Revelation, truſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in his Propoſitions, depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Promiſes, and chearfully reſign your ſelf to be governed by his Laws. It is therefore abſolutely neceſſary to examine well the ſteddineſs of your Faith, the ſeriouſneſs of your Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the purity of your Intentions, and the ſincerity of your Obedience, at leaſt in ſerious reſolution, for the time to come; ſince it is evident that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63466:16"/>without theſe qualifications, you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane this Holy Ordinance, whilſt you make profeſſion ſolemnly of that Religion,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> which you neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, believe, nor practiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I am clearly of your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I think if we communicate in the moſt ſolemn Ordinance of our Religion, we certainly ought to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, believe it, and intend at leaſt to practiſe it. But are we obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged whenſoever we receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to have the Hiſtory, the Principles, and the Duties of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion diſtinctly in our minds? this ſeems to be very hard, and almoſt impoſſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely; you miſtake me very much. Theſe ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidered and examined well, before you preſume to preſent your ſelf, or before you are admitted to the Holy Table: But when you are entred, confirmed, and ſetled in your Religion, there is no neceſſity of ſuch a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection: your Faith will become a habit, and, if you have no doubt of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63466:16"/>any Article, you may boldly make profeſſion of your Faith at any time: and if you are not conſcious of any Vice you wilfully indulge, you may profeſs the ſincerity of your heart, and your reſolution of perſevering in a courſe of univerſal righteouſneſs, without a particular examination of your ſelf upon the ſeveral duties of Chriſtianity. The ordinary prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after you have been throughly inſtructed, and admitted to the Holy Table, is this; Namely, firſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and weigh the doubts and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that are upon your mind concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Branch, or Article of your Religion, if any be, and clear them fully to your ſelf by conſideration, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctruction, and advice. And ſecondly, to obſerve your own particular infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; what thoſe evils are to which you are moſt inclined, and which are apteſt to prevail upon you, and are ſubdued with the greateſt difficulty; and how you may prevent their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for the time to come? what bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, what converſation, what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63466:17"/>what company are apt to expoſe you to temptation? that ſo your humble reſolutions and profeſſions may be well conſidered, and perfectly ſincere, and with particular reſpect to the preſent ſtate of your Soul, with earneſt deſire to be better inſtructed, and reformed by the grace of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>This is but reaſonable indeed, and now I hope I apprehend both the nature of the Sacrament, and the duty of the Communicant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I pray God enable you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it; but there is one thing more that concerns our preparation, which muſt not be omitted, and that is this: Is the Sacrament the Death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord exhibited in proper ſigns? Is our Saviour ſlain before our eyes?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Is his death ſhewed forth, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us till he come,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it? then we ought to raiſe in our minds ſuch a feeling ſenſe, ſuch a ſympathy, ſuch paſſions, affections, and devotions, as the ſight of ſuch a ſtupendous paſſage would have ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, and excited in us, if we had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63466:17"/>been Spectators of it. Had we been the Diſciples of our Saviour, as we now profeſs to be, and had we ſeen Him at his Trial, under his ſcourging, in his Agony, and on the Croſs, ſhould we not have adored and magnified the love of God, that he ſhould ſend His only begotten Son into the world, to bear the puniſhment of <hi>our ſins?</hi> ſhould we not have been aſtoniſhed at the love of our bleſſed Saviour, that He ſhould be contented to diveſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all his glory for our ſakes, and humble himſelf, even to death upon the Croſs, to ſave our ſouls? Would we not have reflected with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon the cauſe of all this grief, to ſo good, ſo great, ſo innocent a Perſon, even the ſins of men? ſhould we not have reſolved for our own part,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> never to contribute to his pain again, but to live in all Obedience, Love, and Gratitude to God, and our Bleſſed Saviour to the end of our lives? ſhould we not have made the moſt paſſionate profeſſions of Fidelity and Conſtancy to him, that has thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63466:18"/>and purchaſed us by His blood? ſhould we not have exerciſed acts of faith, affiance, truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his Word and Promiſes, that if we fulfil our reſolutions, and perform our duty as well as our weak and frail condition will allow, that then we ſhall be accepted of Him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into his Favour, and made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of His Goſpel? and when you have conſidered all theſe things, and underſtand them competently well, and have prayed to God to enlighten your mind, and purge your ſoul from all corrupt affections, from every evil habit that is contrary to his Holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to his moſt pure and righteous Law; that you may ſerve and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, with ſome degrees of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and with a ſincere and perfect heart, then you may aſſure your ſelf, that you are worthy to receive, that your Devotion will be accepted, and your Offering rewarded, that you ſhall have Grace and aſſiſtance from above, to grow better and better, till
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63466:18"/>you come to be perfect in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. The ſum of all is this, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, by the command, and in the name of God, exhibits and offers the bleſſings of the Goſpel to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, and they by receiving the outward ſigns thereof, profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Diſciples of our Lord, that they believe his Doctrine, truſt in his Mediation, hope in his Promiſes, and are reſolved to live according to his Laws. He then who is ſincere in theſe his profeſſions and reſolutions receives worthily; and he who preſents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſuch a ſolemn manner at the Holy Sacrament, making, and being underſtood to make profeſſion of his Chriſtian Faith, and a ſolemn dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf to the obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for ever, when, at the ſame time, he neither underſtands it, regards it, or deſigns to practiſe it, is an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, a Prophaner,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.27.</note> a Blaſphemer of God, and therefore <hi>eats and drinks damnation to himſelf;</hi> incurs the high diſpleaſure of God, and may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expect that the Judgments of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63466:19"/>God ſhould follow him. For <hi>for this cauſe many are ſick and weak among you, and many are fallen aſleep,</hi> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> interprets the damnation ſpoken of before, <hi>v.</hi> 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I thank you with all mine heart, and if I be not too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to you, give me leave to ask you one queſtion more before I go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Pray ask me what you will, for I aſſure you, I am mightily pleas'd to find you ſo inquiſitive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>What is the reaſon then, (ſince, as I underſtand by you, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to every Chriſtian Grace is requiſite in a worthy Communicant) that the Rubrick,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice.</note> and all Divines, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in a particular manner upon Love and Charity, reconciling, and being reconciled to our enemies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>It is well obſerved, they do ſo; yet not as excluſive of any other duties. But indeed there is all the reaſon in the world to remind our Communicants, in a more particular manner, of the duties of Love, and univerſal Charity.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63466:19"/>
               <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe the Religion of our Bleſſed Saviour, which we here ſo ſolemnly profeſs, is founded in Love and Mercy; in the moſt perfect and ineffable goodneſs, which moved Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, by the mediation of our Bleſſed Saviour, to offer eaſie terms of Pardon, Peace, aſſiſtance, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, to all that ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them.
<note place="margin">1 Joh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10. Joh. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rom. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> For <hi>He loved us when we were yet his enemies, and ſent his only begotten ſon into the world, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would but believe in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> And therefore malice, hatred, envy, and evil will, are diſpoſitions, <hi>radically</hi> contrary to Chriſtianity, ſuch as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us utterly unfit to have any thing to do with the ſolemn rites of this Religion.</p>
               <p>Moreover ſecondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Religion it ſelf, that Chriſtian Law, which we here profeſs to embrace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to practiſe, is <hi>a Law of Love.</hi> Univerſal Charity is the principle and life of our Religion, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences the whole, and mingles it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63466:20"/>ſelf with every part thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inſomuch that it is diſtinguiſhed, and deſcrib'd by this ſingle Grace of Love.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 13.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 5.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>att. 22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Joh. 3.9.23.</note> 
                  <hi>For love is the fulfilling of the law,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Paul:</hi> And <hi>Hereby,</hi> ſayes <hi>S. John,</hi> ſpeaking of Love, <hi>we know that we are of the truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him. And this is his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we believe on the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another as he gave us Commandment.</hi> So that all our profeſſions of Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience at the Holy Table, are a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the name of God, and wholly ineffectual to us, ſo long as the temper of our minds, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of our Souls are contrary to the Religion we profeſs. <hi>For unleſs Chriſt be in us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cor. 13.</note> ſays <hi>S. Paul,</hi> that is, the Spirit of Chriſt, the Goodneſs, Love, Meekneſs, Compaſſion, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Forbearance, Condeſcenſion of Him and his Religion, <hi>We are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</hi> Malice indeed, is an indication of a Diabolick Nature, of a mind throughly vicious and degenerate. It is a temper wholly inconſiſtent with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63466:20"/>a true principle of Chriſtianity. <hi>For in this the children of God are manifeſt,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3 10.</note> and the Children of the Devil, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There is a particular fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and congruity in forgiving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and reconciling enemies to the tenor and intention of the Holy Sacrament. God is there exhibited as willing to be reconciled to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſinners: He there renews, and revives his Covenant of Grace, and Mercy to us: Does not reaſon then, that is to ſay, the Law of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the eternal immutable Law of reaſonable Beings, require of us, that we in our capacity ſhould do the ſame? How can we expect that from another, which, in the change of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, we are not willing to do? <hi>Therefore,
<note place="margin">Matt. 7.12.</note> if thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63466:21"/>and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> Which words, though they are ſpoken, by our Saviour, with immediate reſpect to the Peace-Offerings for the Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſins; yet the reaſon holds in all our addreſſes to God for pardon, and has been generally applied by Divines, to the Holy Sacrament. Here, in eſpecial manner, we pray for, and expect his Mercy. But is it reaſonable to hope for ſuch a favour at the hands of God, unleſs we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give ſatisfaction, to our power, for the injuries we have done to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and are ready to forgive offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt our ſelves? Our very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will rebuke ſuch a vain preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. And our Saviour has expreſly taught us, in the Parable of the Lord and his ſteward, that a readineſs to forgive our enemies, is indiſpenſably neceſſary in order to the pardon of our own miſcarriages: The Lord forgave his ſteward a vaſt debt, but he forgetting the goodneſs of his Lord to him, ſues and ſeizes his debtors, and fellow ſervants, for trivial ſums.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63466:21"/>
                  <hi>Wherefore his Lord was wroth,
<note place="margin">Matt. 18. ult.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him to the tormentors, till he ſhould pay all that was due unto him. So likewiſe, ſays our Saviour, ſhall my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father do to you, if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his brother their treſpaſſes.</hi> Nay, he has taught us to acknowledge the reaſonableneſs of it, in our daily prayer,
<note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He then that comes to the Holy Communion with evil will or malice in his heart, muſt needs be out of countenance, as a man that wants the wedding Garment.
<note place="margin">Matt. 22.11.</note> But he whoſe ſoul is free from that unchriſtian vice, he who is an enemy to none, but delights in the happineſs of all, and is ready to aſſiſt whom he may; he who loves his Neighbour as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, may approach with an humble confidence: ſuch a ſuitable temper will give him courage, rational ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and a modeſt aſſurance that his addreſs will be accepted, and his ſins forgiven.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63466:22"/>
               <p>Finally,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and above all, the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular neceſſity of univerſal Charity at the Holy Sacrament is grounded chiefly upon that paſſage of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> (1 Cor. 10.16, 17.) <hi>The Cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which we bleſs, is it not the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the blood of Chriſt? The bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt? for we being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are one bread and one body, for we are all partakers of that one bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 16th Verſe you ſee the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle affirms, that the faithful in the Holy Sacrament communicate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, of the body and blood of Chriſt? <hi>The bread which we break is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> and from thence, in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, he infers the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Love and Unity amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>For we being many are</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> we ought to be) <hi>one bread and one body, why? becauſe we all partake of that one bread,</hi> (or loaſ) which words of the Apoſtle may be underſtood in a double ſenſe, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſignifications and conſtructions of the Holy Sacrament.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63466:22"/>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> 16th. <hi>ver.</hi>
                  </note> as this Supper of our Lord is the Chriſtian Paſſover, and bears an Analogy to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> feaſt upon the Sacrifice of the Paſchal Lamb, which they are together, after the Prieſt had preſented and offered it up to God. And to this the Sacrament ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, and is underſtood as a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual feaſt upon the Sacrifice of our Bleſſed Saviour <hi>whoſe body was offered once for all:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.10.</note> which body and blood we eat in the ſign and figure to the end of the world, by his own Command. <hi>Chriſt our Paſſover</hi> (ſays the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>is ſacrificed for us, therefore let us keep the feaſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7, 8.</p>
               <p>Now thus to eat and drink toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Table,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> 17th. <hi>ver.</hi>
                  </note> and upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our Lord, engages us to one another in the ſtricteſt tyes of Love and Charity, as children of the ſame Father, redeemed by the ſame Lord, co-heirs of the ſame inheritance, fed at the ſame Table, and nouriſhed by the ſame Loaf, which by common acceptation, and fair conſtruction, is both a Token, a Profeſſion, and a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63466:23"/>ſolemn League of Love and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>Again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſecond interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the</hi> 16. v.</note> according to the ſecond Notion of the Holy Sacrament, as it is an inward and ſpiritual grace, a Seal of the New Teſtament, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all the bleſſings of the Goſpel to every individual Perſon that accepts the terms, and will ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the Counterpart, the ſenſe of the 16th. Verſe is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that all who perform the Conditions required of them, ſhall as ſurely enjoy the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of our Saviour's death, as they partake of the viſible ſigns thereof, as they eat the Bread, and drink the Wine, by which it is <hi>ſhewed forth and repreſented. The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> that is, of the benefits of both. Now this conſent to the Conditions of the Goſpel, this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into Covenant with God, this ſincere and chearful dedication of our ſelves to the Government of our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63466:23"/>bleſſed Saviour, which render the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements the Body and Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the receiver is expreſſed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by all ſuch Metaphors, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the moſt intire and perfect uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which can be poſſibly conceived between us, as that between the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the Wife,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.23. Jo. 15.1. Jo. 10. 1 Cor. 12.27.</note> the Vine and the Branches, the Shepherd and the Flock, the Head and Members, the Soul and Body; which Unity is not natural and perſonal, that were Blaſphemy to imagine, but Intellectual and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: one Vital Principle moves them, one ſpirit acts and inhabits in them both: our Saviour and his true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples have the ſame opinions of what is good and evil, the ſame affections to every thing that is good, the ſame will to proceed and act according to the moſt perfect reaſon.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.10.</note> 
                  <hi>If Chriſt be in you,</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>the body is dead.</hi> Now the manner of His being in us, is explained in the former Verſe,
<note place="margin">V. 9.</note> by His temper, ſpirit, and diſpoſition. <hi>For if any man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his;</hi> as in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63466:24"/>place it is explained by his <hi>Mind, That the ſame Mind may be in us, which was in him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.5. Eph. 3.17.</note> And again, <hi>That He may dwell in our hearts by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now from this ſpiritual Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſecond interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the</hi> 17. v.</note> and thoſe who worthily receive the Sacrament, that is, who have reſigned themſelves to the obedience of the Goſpel, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle infers the moſt intire and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect unity of the whole body of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians amongſt themſelves. Ye are, ſays he, united to Chriſt, by eating His Body, and drinking His Blood, He becomes a principle of new life to every one that receives the Sacrament as he ought to do. Now, ſays he, the union is the very ſame, and upon the ſame account, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the faithful amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For, carrying on the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, <hi>We being many are one body, and one bread,
<note place="margin">V. 17.</note> becauſe we are all partakers of that one bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We all receive nouriſhment from the ſame root, and are therefore vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally united to one another; <hi>We are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63466:24"/>all made to drink,</hi> (ſpeaking of the Cup in the holy Sacrament) <hi>into one ſpirit.</hi> All which, laying aſide the Allegory, is thus to be underſtood, that foraſmuch as all ſincere and faithful Chriſtians have entred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ſame Society, underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame inſtitution and rule of life, conſent and agree in the ſame mind, affections, deſires, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fation, therefore they are morally u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to one another, as well as to our bleſſed Saviour. For our Saviour is not divided, He is one and the ſame in his Nature, his Life, his Goſpel, his Laws, and Promiſes; ſo that if innumerable individuals devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the belief of his Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the love and obedience of his inſtructions, if they reſign themſelves, their wills and affections to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<note place="margin">Jo. 17.21</note> whereby they become in a Moral ſenſe united to him; theſe of neceſſity, by the ſame Moral unity, are joyned and knit amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. One common ſoul and ſpirit acts and influences them all, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63466:25"/>have parted from their own private will and conduct, and reſolved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the guidance of another, whoſe Law is immoveably perfect, and the ſame to every particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. There muſt be therefore an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, and intire conſent in their opinions, deſires, and courſe of life, as being derived from one and the ſame unalterable Law.
<note place="margin">Iph. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>They grow up into him in all things,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, which is the head even Christ.</hi> And thus the unity of all ſincere and faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians with <hi>Christ,</hi> and with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be eaſily underſtood of all: and yet it is as real, as ſtrict, and proper as the Metaphor, in the Text before us, by which it is expreſt: namely, the unity of innumerable Particles of Flower (by the balm or leaven which pervades and binds them all) in one Lump or Loaf. <hi>For we being many are one body, and one bread,
<note place="margin">V. 17.</note> for we are all partakers of that one bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Concluſion then is this, that if all the faithful Chriſtians upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63466:25"/>earth, are as the ſeveral parts of the ſame loaf, if they are members one of another, if they receive their vital influence from the ſame root,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.20.</note> if they are moved and acted by the ſame principle, then we ought, that is, we muſt, we can do no other than love one another intirely: no love like that which ſympathy and conſent of will creates: or to ſpeak more properly, love is not the creature of ſympathy and conſent, but ſympathy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Will, are Love; they are the thing it ſelf, they cannot be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. And therefore without Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without intire and perfect Love amongſt our ſelves, we cannot be united to Chriſt, we cannot have ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his Body or drunk his Blood. The Elements will be no more, to ſuch as theſe, nay leſs, than common bread and wine. We cannot be the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the myſtical body of Chriſt, ſo long as we are ſeparated from one another by the leaſt degree of malice and evil will, <hi>for no man ever hated his own fleſh. He then that loves not,
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4 8.</note> knows
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63466:26"/>not God,</hi> (has no true principle of Religion) <hi>for God is love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon all theſe accounts it is, that the Holy Sacrament has been always eſteemed <hi>a token of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, a bond of Charity, and a ſymbol of peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hence it was, that in former times the Communicants brought their Offerings to the Miniſter, Fruits of the earth, or any Viands for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, which, when the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was ended, were eaten as a common feaſt, by all degrees and ranks promiſcuouſly, without reſpect to place or quality. And this was the <hi>feaſt of Charity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pet. 2.13.</note> mentioned by <hi>S. Jude v.</hi> 12. and was concluded with a kiſs, in token of entire and perfect friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>But theſe pure and innocent Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies being ſoon abuſed, were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards diſuſed: Nevertheleſs we have ſomething like them ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in our Church, namely, in the Collection that is ordinarily made for the poor; and, after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63466:26"/>in eating and drinking what remains of the Conſecrated Elements in the Church,
<note place="margin">Rubr.</note> without diſtinction of perſons, but, as the cuſtom is, the meaneſt perſons are invited to be the chief partakers of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I hope I underſtand you, and I am heartily glad that I did not receive before I was inſtructed; and I find upon the matter, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires both time and retirement to prepare our ſelves as we ought to do, and the firſt time more eſpecially; but I will endeavour, by God's aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, to follow your directions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>You have made a very good inference from our whole diſcourſe; the reaſon of the action, and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of this moſt ſacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the ſeveral parts of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which it has reſpect to, require a very ſtrict examination of our Knowledge, Repentance, Affections, purpoſes and deſires, that ſo our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the thing, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of our mind, may bear a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the outward action, to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63466:27"/>deſign, the words, and the geſtures of the ſervice. Our devotion, as you have heard, is to be exerciſed upon every part of Chriſtianity, our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular defects are here to be bewailed; the ſeveral graces of Faith, Hope, and Love, univerſal Love towards God and Man, are to be exerted in this ſolemnity: and therefore it is very neceſſary to withdraw our ſelves from the world, and retire into our ſelves, ſome time before we receive.</p>
               <p>That we may recollect the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and the duties, the bleſſings and the promiſes of our Religion; that we may examine the ſtate of our Soul; what neceſſary Article of Faith we doubt of, or do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; what evil habit remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified, or is moſt unwilling to be ſubdued; what is the <hi>ſin that ſo eaſily beſets us,</hi> that has the advantage of our natural complexion, violent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, or preſent profit: what methods we have taken, or may take for the future, to ſubdue it; what improvements we have made ſince
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63466:27"/>we laſt received, and how we have kept our reſolutions.</p>
               <p>That we may ſufficiently bewail our failings,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and take pleaſure and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in our proficiency.</p>
               <p>That we may excite and ſtir up our devotions by proper Meditations.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Theſe are weighty matters, yet very neceſſary, and therefore require a previous conſideration.</p>
               <p>But to ſay how long, how many hours, or days, or weeks a man ought to ſpend in Meditation and Prayer, before he may preſume to receive; or to what degree of Knowledge and Virtue he muſt attain, is both impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and unneceſſary. Do you but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that competent knowledge, and great integrity, with an hearty deſire to grow in Grace, and the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18.</note> is the true preparation of the Soul, and you ſhall be able, with Sobriety, to judge for your ſelf. He that wants this, is not fit to receive; but he that is thus qualified, is a worthy Communicant, though
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63466:28"/>his knowledge may not be ſo diſtinct and clear, or his virtues ſo ſhining and perfect, as ſome other Chriſtians poſſibly may be. Has not God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged perſons of weak Faith, and a frail virtue, provided it be true, to hope for his acceptance?
<note place="margin">Aatt. 12.20.</note> For <hi>he will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax,</hi> (ſays our Saviour) that is, he will ſupport it and inflame it by the influences of his Grace; if we have but the firſt beginnings of Holineſs, an hearty liking of it, and deſire after it; he will nouriſh it, and bring it to perfection.
<note place="margin">Aatt 7.7.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>For to them that knock it ſhall be opened. They that ask ſhall have. They that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs ſhall be filled.</hi> No man therefore that is inquiſitive to know, and ſincere in practice, has any reaſon to be diſcouraged. For the Grace and aſſiſtance which God has promiſed, he beſtows, and infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into the hearts of men, as by the immediate influences of his Spirit upon the Soul, ſo eſpecially, through his Word and Sacraments. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63466:28"/>we cannot be too well prepared, but we may be too ſcrupulous about the degrees of Knowledge and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which are the indiſpenſable conditions of our acceptance. We may prevent our growth in Grace, by thinking our ſelves unfit to uſe the means thereof. An hearty deſire of perfection, with ſuch endeavours, Improvements, Devotions and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, as our capacity and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity will permit, intitle us to the uſe, and to the benefits of the Holy Sacraments. For how could they be ſaid to be the <hi>means</hi> of Grace, if none but perſons already veſted with it <hi>in great degrees,</hi> were allowed to uſe them. So that the ſincere, though imperfect Chriſtian, at the preſent, has a particular propriety in the Holy Sacrament, becauſe they are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, to be the means of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that, which theſe eſpecially want. <hi>For I am not come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 9.12, 13.</note> ſays our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance.</hi> And again, <hi>The whole need not a Phyſician, but the ſick.</hi> Not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63466:29"/>that there are any ſo <hi>righteous,</hi> as not to need <hi>Repentance,</hi> or ſo <hi>whole</hi> as not to need a <hi>Phyſician;</hi> but the more confirmed and eſtabliſht Men are in a courſe of Obedience to God, the more they are under the power of Religion, and the longer they have ſo continued; Theſe, comparatively ſpeaking, have the leſs occaſion to uſe the means.</p>
               <p>I ſay not this to encourage careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or indifference in the worſhip of God, in any. God knows the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the beſt are ſo great, and ſo many, that there is little fear of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting a good Man from the worſhip of God, becauſe of the comfort and ſupport he feels therein, and the great neceſſity in this ſtate of uncertainty and war that he finds thereof: But ſince our Saviour allows it, I would, by His own ſimilitudes, expel and diſſipate all fatal ſcruples out of the minds of the ſincere, though young Beginners in Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Par.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I thank you for your pains, and I hope they are not ill beſtowed;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63466:29"/>by the Grace of God you ſhall ſee the good effect thereof in a little time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Ay, that is the end of all. I pray God confirm your Reſolutions, and be ſure you let me ſee you as often as you can, that I may explain, or enlarge upon any Article of our Diſcourſe, or refreſh your Memory, as occaſion may require.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="proper_prayers">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63466:30"/>
            <head>Proper Prayers, ſuited to the foregoing Account of the Holy Sacrament.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Preparatory Prayer.</head>
               <p>OAlmighty God! although <hi>thy Councils are unſearchable,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> and thy ways paſt finding out,</hi> tho' neither I <hi>nor the Angels of thy preſence ſhall ever comprehend</hi> the <hi>myſtery</hi> of Man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption thro' Jeſus Chriſt;
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.12.</note> yet it is enough for me, that thus it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; and therefore I believe with all mine heart, I adore the myſtery, and reſolve my hope and truſt into the merits of the Croſs. I will now and ever implore thy Pardon, Grace, and Aſſiſtance, for His ſake alone, whoſe Body was broken, and whoſe Blood was ſhed for the Remiſſion of my ſins, mine only Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. And O that I might meet my Lord this day, in the appointed Signs, and Sacrament of his Paſſion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63466:30"/>with an heart as ſted faſt in the Faith, as if I had ſeen his Miracles; as full of Love, as if I had been healed of my diſeaſes by his Power; as full of Joy, as if Himſelf had ſaid unto me, <hi>Be of good chear, thy ſins are all forgiven;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 9.2.</note> as conſtant in my Reſolutions againſt all Impiety and ſin, as if I had ſeen my Lord in his Agony, and heard Him ſay, <hi>My God, my God, why hast Thou forſaken me!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 27.46.</note> O Lord encourage my ſincere deſires, and enable me to perform the intended duties, with theſe, and all ſuch holy diſpoſitions as Thou requireſt of me; aſſiſt my weakneſs by thy power, ſupport and ſtrengthen all thoſe Graces which Thou haſt begun, and perfect them, at laſt, in habits of Obedience, Love, and Praiſe through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Ejaculation upon the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Bread.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord, I am a ſinful man,
<note place="margin">Matt. 8.8.</note> not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy that thou ſhouldſt come under my
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63466:31"/>roof.</hi> O cleanſe my ſoul from all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity and filth, make me fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſo glorious a gueſt, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and dwell in me for ever, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A ſhort Ejaculation upon receiving of the Cup.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord,
<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> I believe, help thou mine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief;</hi> that the Bread which I eat, and the Wine which I drink, thus bleſſed and given by thy Command, may be indeed the Body and Blood of Chriſt to me, the Seal of my Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and the earneſt of Eternal life, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid immediately after you have received the Elements.</head>
               <p>O Moſt merciful God and Father! How wonderful is Thy love to me a wretched ſinner, that Thou now vouchſafeſt to receive me as a gueſt to thine own Table, and haſt fed me with <hi>the Bread of Heaven!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 6.55.</note> That thou
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63466:31"/>ſhouldſt make an offer of peace and reconciliation to me! That Thou ſhouldſt never be weary of ſhewing mercy! That the blood of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhould be ſalutary ſtill, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited for ever, to the relief of all that are willing to be healed! <hi>Lord, what is man that thou art ſo mindful of him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.4.</note> or the Son of Man that Thou ſo regardeſt him!</hi> O make me worthy of this ineſtimable bleſſing; purifie my thoughts, rectifie my will, ſanctifie mine affections, ſtrengthen my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, that I may go on <hi>from one degree of grace unto another,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.28. Mat. 25.23.</note> till I come to be perfect in Christ Jeſus:</hi> that I may improve my Talent, and be the better ſenſible for every Sacrament I receive, till my Faith ſhall at laſt be perfected in Viſion, and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thy Body and Blood, ſhall be finally reſolved into the full en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of thine Eternal Deity, O Bleſſed Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63466:32"/>
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid in your Cloſet after your return from the Holy Communion.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God!
<note place="margin">Pſ. 7.9. Rev. 2.23. Pſ. 51.6.</note> 
                  <hi>That ſearcheſt the hearts, and trieſt the reins of men! Thou that requireſt truth in the inner parts!</hi> O purge my ſoul from all Hypocriſie and guile, that I may now, and always, ſerve thee with that ſincerity and purity as I ought to do! O Lord, I hope my inward ſelf, my very ſoul and heart did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite the Praiſes, Prayers, and Vows of my Tongue this day before thee. <hi>O thou that remembreſt whereof we are made,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 103 14.</note> and conſidereſt that we are but men!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb 4.15.</note> O Thou our great High Prieſt, <hi>who art touched with the feeling of our infirmities,</hi> accept of my good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and forgive the coldneſs of my Devotions, and the remiſneſs of my mind, the wandring of my thoughts, and the many imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this, and of all mine Holy things! and, O Lord, I beſeech thee continue upon my ſoul that Holy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63466:32"/>diſpoſition, that Religious ſenſe, which, by thy Grace, I have been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this day; that I may be united to thy ſelf in the ſame affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deſires;
<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>that my life may be hid with Chriſt in God, that when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in Glory;</hi> to whom with the Father and the Holy Spirit be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed all Honour, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty, Dominion and Obedience, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="general_prayers">
            <head>General Prayers to be ſaid at any time.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Confeſſion of Sins.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God!
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Creator, and wiſe diſpoſer of all things;</hi> Thou haſt been very gracious unto me from my youth up until now; Thou haſt bleſſed me with every thing that is neceſſary for the inſtruction of my ſoul, and for the ſupport and pleaſure of my life. O
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63466:33"/>what obligations haſt thou laid upon me, by thy particular Grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour towards me, to ſerve thee all the days of my life with a perfect heart?</p>
               <p>What then ſhall I ſay unto Thee, O Thou that art the Judge of men? How have I requited thee for all the benefits Thou haſt done unto me? I bluſh and am aſhamed to appear before thee;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 139.8. Amos 9.2, 3, 4. Pſ. 51.3.</note> but I cannot <hi>fly from thy preſence; I will therefore acknowledge my tranſgreſſions, and mine iniquities I will not hide.</hi> How have I employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my childhood and youth in trifles? How has my mind been filled and poſſeſs'd with vanity? How impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and yet how frivolous have I been in my deſires, how fooliſh in all mine actions? How inſenſible of my duty to thy Sacred Majeſty, how cold in my Devotions, how negligent of Inſtruction, how indifferent to ſober Counſels? How have I preferred the profit, the pomp, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the World, before my duty to God, my neighbour, and my ſelf?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63466:33"/>O Lord, I am very ſenſible, that my ſins are more in number, than the hairs of my head, more in weight than I am able to bear. Mine only hope is in Thy mercy, mine only refuge are Thy Gracious Promiſes of pardon and favour to repenting ſinners, through the Merits and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Jeſus Chriſt, our only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Pardon.</head>
               <p>O Moſt Holy and Righteous God! I humbly proſtrate my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Glorious Majeſty, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and bewail my many and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſins, which I have committed againſt Thee:
<note place="margin">Jam. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I do not know how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten I have offended.</hi> The ſenſe of my miſcarriages is very ſharp upon my ſpirit, and the apprehenſion of Thy juſt diſpleaſure is very terrible. But <hi>Thou haſt invited all that travel,
<note place="margin">Matt. 11 28.</note> and are heavy laden, to come unto Thee, and haſt promiſed to refreſh them. Thou haſt laid help upon one that is mighty to ſave,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 89.19</note>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:63466:34"/>even <hi>the Lamb that was ſlain from the beginning of the World:
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h. 1.</note> He has born our griefs and carried our ſorrows,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i. 53.</note> and on Him is laid the iniquities of us all.</hi> Lord, of thine infinite mercies, waſh away my ſins in the blood of my dear Redeemer; nail them to his Croſs, bury them in his Grave, that they may never riſe in Judgment againſt me, to accuſe and terrifie my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence here, or condemn me to everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhment in the life to come, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Reſolution.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God! I acknowledge and adore Thy Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, that Thou haſt made me a reaſonable Creature, that I am not driven by neceſſity, as other Beings are,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> but am created in the <hi>Image of God himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O how juſt and reaſonable is it, that we ſhould glorifie our bountiful Creator with all the faculties which He has given us? O God, I bewail
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63466:34"/>mine own defects of Duty towards Thee; I have not improved mine opportunities of knowledge; I have been contented to know but little, and have practiſed leſs; my mind has been employed and ſatisfied in trifling objects, my will has follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after vanity, and <hi>God has not been in all my thoughts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But now, O Lord, I am very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my folly, as well as of my ſin, and I am reſolved for the time to come,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> to <hi>run the way of Thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when Thou ſhalt enlarge mine heart.</hi> I do moſt ſincerely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly <hi>offer and preſent my ſelf, my ſoul and body,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> a lively reaſonable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice unto Thee:</hi> I unfeignedly reſolve <hi>that ſin ſhall no more have dominion over me,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> I will not yield my members inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs to ſin, but I will yield my ſelf to God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 96.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> I will endeavour to affect my mind with the <hi>beauty of holineſs,</hi> till I Love by thine affections, chuſe what Thou propoſeſt, believe what Thou reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, expect Thy promiſes, and intirely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63466:35"/>reſign my ſelf to the obedience of thy Law: Lord, of thy Goodneſs accept mine offering, have mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon me, pity mine infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conſider my Contrition, accept my Repentance, encourage my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, and reſtore me to Thy Grace and favour, through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord and only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Act of Hope.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! Thou art Infinite in all Perfections, the Author and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all the ſcattered excellencies in the World!
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 1.16.</note> as Thou art juſt to puniſh Wickedneſs,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 145.9.</note> ſo <hi>Thy Mercy is over all thy Works: Thou remembrest that we are but men;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 103.14.</note> Thou conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the various temptations, to which we are expoſed, the weakneſs of our reaſon, the violence of our paſſions, <hi>the treachery of our hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 17.9.</note> the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of our Bodies, and all the imperfections of our preſent ſtate. <hi>Thou art not therefore extreme to mark
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63466:35"/>what we do amiſs; Thou art ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, full of compaſſion,
<note place="margin">Exo. 34.4</note> and abundant in goodneſs and truth;
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.23.</note> Thou haſt no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the death of him that dies, but, if at any time the wicked will turn away from his ſins, and do that which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and right, Thou haſt promiſed that he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity ſhall not be his ruine. Thou, O bleſſed Jeſus,
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.14 Heb. 9.12 2 Pet. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1 Cor. 6.20. 1 Joh. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Heb. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> haſt purchaſed pardon and redemption for us, at the price of Thy precious blood; Thou art the propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for our ſins, our Advocate and only Mediator, who art able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, all that come unto God by Thee, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thou ever liveſt to make interceſſion for us.</hi> I know, O Lord, <hi>that never a word ſhall fail that Thou haſt ſpoken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.56.</note> and therefore I will never add the ſin of diſtruſt to the number of mine offences; but I will always worſhip before my God, with the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable thoughts, the moſt worthy apprehenſions I can conceive or frame. Lord, make me truly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for what is paſt, perfect in the purpoſes of mine heart, ſincere in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63466:36"/>profeſſions of my Tongue, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to live thereafter for the time to come, and then I will humbly hope in the promiſes of thy Goſpel, and <hi>ſerve thee without fear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk. 1.74.</note> O bleſſed God, by the aſſiſtance of thy moſt holy and eternal Spirit. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Divine Aſſiſtance and increaſe of Grace.</head>
               <p>MOST Glorious and Bleſſed God! Thou art Infinite in all perfections, thy Will is pure, and all thine Excellencies are unchangeable. But though thou haſt been pleaſed to derive upon us ſome ſmall degrees of thy glorious Nature, though we act for the ſake of ſuch ends as we our ſelves propoſe and chuſe; yet our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties are weak, our ſenſitive appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites impoſe upon our reaſon, <hi>The law of our members prevails upon the law of our mind,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om 7.15, 16, &amp;c.</note> that we cannot do the thing that we would.</hi> O work in me, O Lord, what thou wouldſt have me <hi>both to will and do:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hil. 2.13.</note> aſſiſt me by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63466:36"/>thy Grace, that the power of evil habits may decay and dye in me, that the life of God and all the Graces of the Holy Spirit, may grow more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous and ſtrong! <hi>Break not, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.20</note> the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax,</hi> but aſſiſt my weakneſs, ſtrengthen my faint deſires, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage my ſincerity, confirm my Faith, inflame my Love, cheriſh mine Hope, and enlarge my Charity: ſupport me under all my conflicts, and carry me through all temptations, that I may chearfully do and ſuffer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever pleaſes thee.
<note place="margin">Matt. 5 6. Pſal. 63.1.84.2.42.1. Phil. 3.14.</note> O how <hi>I hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs! how my ſoul longeth after God!</hi> how chearfully could <hi>I leave all things that hinder me behind, and preſs forwards for the prize of the high calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt, if by any means I may attain the reſurrection of the dead.</hi> O perfect what thou haſt begun,
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.47. Gal. 4.19. Pſ. 73.24.</note> 
                  <hi>dwell in mine heart by faith, and form thy ſelf in me. Guide me by thy counſels here, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me at laſt into thine everlaſting glory,</hi> through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:63466:37"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a due intention of Mind, in the Celebration of Religious Duties.</head>
               <p>O Father of Mercies, and God of all our Conſolations! It was Thine own eſſential Goodneſs that firſt inclined thee to create us, that thou mighteſt communicate thy ſelf unto us, and exerciſe thy Grace and Bounty upon us. Thou haſt given us all the aſſurances that our hearts can wiſh, <hi>That thou delighteſt to do us good,</hi> and that <hi>thine ears are open to our prayers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet 3.12.</note> How juſtly then art thou the <hi>deſire</hi> and the <hi>Worſhip of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> O that I could praiſe thee with underſtanding, and recount thine Excellencies with that Senſe and Adoration as I ought! O that I could make my Prayers unto thee with a perfect Heart, with true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and ſutable endeavour! that in all the Solemnities of Religion, I could approach thy preſence with ſuch an holy frame, with ſuch a temper and affection of mind as the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63466:37"/>duty may require! But, O Lord, I cannot enough bewail mine own formality and deadneſs in things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Spiritual. How difficult do I find it, to raiſe in my mind a lively ſenſe of God, even in the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn duties? How hard it is to bring my Soul to ſuch a perfect Unity, to ſuch an intire concurrence as it ought to have with the outward celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion? But, O bleſſed Jeſus, who once didſt pity and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the infirmities of thine own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.45.</note> 
                  <hi>who could not watch with thee an hour,</hi> have mercy upon me! Warm mine Affections by the irradiations of thy Love, refine my Nature, and raiſe me above the body. Enlighten my Mind that I may know Thee; correct the perverſeneſs of my Will, that I may chearfully obey Thee; mortifie all mine inordinate deſires, that I may prefer and chuſe Thee; heal all my bodily diſtempers, eaſe my worldly cares, ſubdue mine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly paſſions, and preſerve me from too ſtrong temptations, that my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63466:38"/>Mind may be always ſteddy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, always fit to ſerve Thee here, that I may ſing an eternal Hallelujah to thy Praiſe hereafter, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to be ſaid, by well meaning perſons, under any dejection or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencies of Mind.</head>
               <p>O Moſt Merciful God and Father! <hi>Thou correcteſt,
<note place="margin">Jer. 10.24.</note> but it is with judgment not thine anger, that thou ſhouldſt bring us to nothing;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> thou cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneſt every ſon whom thou doſt receive:</hi> All the evils that we ſuffer in the world, are the directions of thy Wiſdom for <hi>our Good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note> I therefore bleſs thy Holy Name for all thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly corrections, wherewith in Mercy thou haſt ever viſited me. And I humbly implore thy Divine Aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that I may now behave my ſelf with the moſt intire and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſignation to thy Will, under that confuſion, fear, and terror of mind, which thou art pleaſed to lay
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63466:38"/>upon me. I rejoyce in the midſt of this ſore affliction, (as it is a token of thy care and Love) how ſeverely ſoever it may affect me. Lord, bring me nearer to thy ſelf, and preſerve me ſtedfaſt in my duty to the end, how ſharp ſoever the means may be. But, O moſt gracious Father! if the hiding of thy Countenance from me for a time, has wrought thoſe happy effects upon me, for which thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs did deſign it; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore me, O reſtore me, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, to a ſenſe of thy Love, to peace in my Mind again.
<note place="margin">Pſ 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I am weary of my groaning, all the night long do I water my couch with my tears,</hi> my Soul is diſquieted within me, ſunk down into the duſt of death, even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pit of hell. <hi>Viſit me, O God,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 106.4.</note> with thy ſalvation,</hi> cauſe thine Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to deſcend into mine heart, that he may defend and guard me in all my tryals, ſupport and quiet my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected Mind:
<note place="margin">Iſ. 50 2. 59.1. Matt 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy hand is not ſhortned that it cannot ſave; ſay but the word, O Lord, and thy ſervant ſhall be healed.</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:63466:39"/>O how would I magnifie thy Glory, imitate thy Life, and obey thy Will, if Thou ſhouldſt be pleaſed to truſt me with Health and Peace again.</p>
               <p>Lord, pardon, and hear the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of thy ſervant; my heart is full,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.4.55.5.142.1. Pſal. 60.1. Lam. 5.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>my ſoul alſo is ſore troubled. Lord, how long wilt thou puniſh me? O turn Thee again, and have mercy upon me; conſider my complaint, and let my cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come unto Thee!</hi> O how chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully would I do or ſuffer any thing, whereby I might teſtifie the ſincerity of mine Adoration, Love, and Duty to Thy Sacred Majeſty! <hi>I have none in Heaven but God,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.25.</note> and there is none upon Earth that I deſire in compariſon of Thee!</hi> O when ſhall I feel <hi>that joy and peace</hi> in my mind, which Thou haſt promiſed to <hi>thoſe that Love Thy Law?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ 119 165.</note> O when wilt thou diſpel thoſe clouds of diffidence and fear, which depreſs and trouble me, even now, that I find in my ſelf the moſt ſincere deſires to do my duty in the World! <hi>Yet not my will,
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.42.</note> O Lord, but Thine be done; here I am, do with me whatſoever
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:63466:39"/>pleaſes Thee; Though Thou ſhouldſt ſlay me, yet will I truſt in Thee.</hi> I throw my ſelf into the Arms of Thy mercy, beſeeching Thee <hi>to lay no more upon me, than Thou ſhalt enable me to bear;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> and all I beg upon the alone Account of the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Protection, with Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God! Thou art the Almighty Father of the world; I was created by thy Power, and am preſerved by thy Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: I am truly ſenſible of Thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Grace and favour towards me, in all the periods and ſtates of life, thro' which I have paſſed
<note place="margin">* <hi>Mention here the particular bleſſings of your condition, whether in pious Parents, or in hopeful Children, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous eſtate, faithful friends, bountiful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors, good buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, diſcreet or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wife,</hi> &amp;c.</note>. O bleſſed God, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect my mind as it ought to be, with a ſenſe of thy boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and beneficence, that I may rely upon Thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the time to come; that I may be wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63466:40"/>to Thy moſt bleſſed Will, and fully ſatisfied under all Thy diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards me. Endue me, O Lord, with all thoſe gifts and graces, that may enable me to acquit my ſelf as I ought to do, in all the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life, which thou ſhalt be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call me to; open mine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, rectifie mine errors, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my diligence, ſtrengthen my faith, and with my capacities inlarge my Charity, that Thou mayſt ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be gracious to me, to direct my Counſel, to preſerve my health, to guide my hand, and to bleſs me in all my ways and works, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, in whoſe moſt holy name and words, I conclude mine imperfect prayers, ſaying,
<q>Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:63466:40"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. xxii. 37, 38, 39.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Jeſus ſaid unto him, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind.</p>
                  <p>This is the firſt and great Commandment.</p>
                  <p>And the ſecond is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Immortality of the Soul, and a future ſtate of Bliſs or Miſery, according as our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the fleſh have been good or evil; are the common Notions, the indeleble Opinions, the univerſal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Mankind. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a diſtinct and perfect knowledge of Religion, or of ſuch an Inſtitution of Faith and Manners, as will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be accepted of God, procure his favour here, and everlaſting bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs in the Life to come, is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the higheſt concernment to us.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63466:41"/>No reaſonable Man, that believes a future Judgment, with the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Rewards and Puniſhments, can find any peace or contentment in his Mind, till by a clear underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his duty, and a firm reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to fulfil it, he has founded to himſelf, a rational hope of a happy life in the other World.</p>
            <p>But though the thing it ſelf has been always ſteddily believed, yet a conſiſtent regular account of this fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Life was never ſtated; nor the methods by which it might certainly be obtained, which ſo much concerns us, diſcovered to the World: till the <hi>light of the Gentiles, and the glory of Iſrael appeared, to give us the knowledge of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even the <hi>Jews</hi> had no diſtinct and clear conception of the Life to come. The opinions of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerning it, (who were the moſt zealous aſſertors of it) were very abſurd and ſenſual; inſomuch that <hi>Joſephus</hi> compares the heaven of the <hi>Phaniſees</hi> to that of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:63466:41"/>dream'd of fortunate Iſlands, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all imaginable delights of the Body, quick and more curious appetites, and more perfect objects of ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>But by the Miniſtry of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, <hi>Life and Immortality are brought to light,</hi> propoſed intelligibly, and aſſerted with Divine Authority. Hence the Phariſees having heard of the Wiſdom of our Saviour, that he had put the Sadducees to ſilence, clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and was able to anſwer all the doubts and queſtions concerning the life to come, ſent a Lawyer, from amongſt themſelves,
<note place="margin">V. 35.</note> to make an experiment of his Judgment, who enquires of our Saviour, under the ſtyle of <hi>Maſter; Which is the great Commandment? Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto him, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind, and thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text is a general Account of the way and method, whereby we may attain everlaſting life; of ſuch
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:63466:42"/>a converſation and courſe of action here, as will procure to us everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bleſſedneſs in the world to come.</p>
            <p>And all the Duties, Qualities, and Habits, which are required of us, as conditions of Eternal life, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by our Saviour under theſe Two Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The firſt reſpects our duty towards God: <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The ſecond reſpects our duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbour: <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I begin with the firſt of theſe, which reſpects our Duty towards God. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind: This is the firſt and great Commandment.</hi> And in the handling of this copious Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I <hi>ſhall</hi> confine my thoughts to this following Method.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſhall explain the terms, and give you a more general account of the nature of the duty; and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into which it is reſolved.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:63466:42"/>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I ſhall conſider the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts, the neceſſary acts and exerciſes <hi>of Love to God.</hi> Firſt, <hi>With all the Heart, and with all the Soul:</hi> And Secondly, <hi>With all the Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I ſhall conſider upon what Accounts, the <hi>Love of God with all the Heart, and with all the Soul, and with all the Mind,</hi> may be ſaid to be the <hi>Firſt and Great Commandment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I ſhall perſwade, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you to the practice of this duty, and the purſuit of this habit of <hi>Love to God,</hi> by ſeveral motives, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and implied in this one word, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly and Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I ſhall make Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the whole.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Explication of the terms, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the nature of the duty in the general, and the Principles into which it is reſolved: <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God.</hi> To <hi>Love,</hi> is to take delight and pleaſure in the Object, with a deſire of ſuch an enjoyment of it, as the nature of the thing will
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:63466:43"/>bear, and Reaſon will permit; and the cauſes, or reaſons of ſuch Delight and Deſire, are only two, (however various the objects, about which they are exerciſed, may be) namely, an opinion of perſonal excellency in the object it ſelf, or a ſenſe of kindneſs, or benefits received from it. Theſe are the onely Principles of Love; theſe are the onely cauſes of all the delight and deſire in the world, that is voluntary and choſen. Perſons, 'tis true, may be, and very frequently are miſtaken, in their apprehenſions of beauty and goodneſs, whereby this beſt, and moſt agreeable paſſion of love, is too often exerciſed upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy objects, purſued and enjoyed after an unreaſonable manner. But notwithſtanding that, whether the object be wiſely choſen or fooliſhly, whether the beauty apprehended, be real, or imaginary, whereſoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and deſire are, there beauty, or goodneſs in the object, is, however, apprehended and ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>And from this general account of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:63466:43"/>the nature and Principles of Love, we may moſt firmly eſtabliſh the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Love to God. Wherefore then <hi>to Love the Lord our God,</hi> is ſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the excellencies of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature, his abſolute perfections in themſelves, and his infinite grace, and goodneſs towards us, as that we moſt ſincerely and heartily admire and adore his Majeſty, and earneſtly deſire the moſt intimate enjoyment of Him, and the moſt perfect union with Him, that we are capable of. This is the nature of the Duty in the general.</p>
            <p>And the Qualifications with which it ought to be exerciſed, are three, <hi>with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text is taken out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thine Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Might.</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.27.</note> and St. <hi>Luke</hi> expreſs it, <hi>with all thy Strength.</hi> And becauſe of this indifferent vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the phraſe, and becauſe the ſame thing is ſometimes expreſſed by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:63466:44"/>one of theſe phraſes only, as <hi>with all thy Heart,</hi> 1 Sam. 7.3. Sometimes the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> without the <hi>Mind</hi> or Strength, as in the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.3. Therefore ſome Expoſitors conſider the Heart, the Soul, and Mind, as words of the ſame, or of equal ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, accumulated only to preſs, and inculcate the duty more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon us, but not as a Climax of perfection in the practice of it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we may obſerve a real and material difference, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe and acceptation of the words, expreſſing the degrees of Intention, and deſire, in the acts and operations of the Soul; and becauſe it will very much adminiſter to the juſt explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the duty, therefore I ſhall preſume, and with good authority, to conſider the <hi>Heart,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Mind,</hi> as qualifications of gradual Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as a Scale of Perfection, in the practice and exerciſe of Love to God.</p>
            <p>And firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>With all thy Heart:</hi> By the <hi>Heart,</hi> according to the uſual ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:63466:44"/>of that Metaphor, we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Integrity, Sincerity</hi> of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Ye have obeyed from the heart,</hi> Rom. 6.17. <hi>the form of doctrine that was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered you,</hi> that is, <hi>ſincerely,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>hypocriſie.</hi> And innumerable other places.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>with all thy Soul,</hi> that is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> with Underſtanding and Knowledge; that our Love of God be not only <hi>Sincere,</hi> but grounded well, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Cauſes proper and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; not with Paſſion only, but with Judgment. The Soul here may be underſtood of Reaſon and Diſcretion, whereby we diſtinguiſh of Good and Evil, baſe and worthy, and to whoſe determinations the Will, Deſires, and inſtruments of Action are obedient.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>with all thy Mind.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> By the <hi>Mind,</hi> may be underſtood the more Spiritual Principle in Man, whereby he feels, and enjoys the truth of ſuch Propoſitions, as Reaſon, by comparing one thing with another, ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. Reaſon is, as it were, an Artificial, Mechanical deduction of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:63466:45"/>Concluſions from Premiſes, but the Mind enjoys them <hi>really,</hi> by an intire agreement with the Propoſition. And upon this account the wicked, in Scripture, are ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as are able to collect the truths of Religion, or any other Propoſitions, by Scholaſtick inference; but the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Regenerate have an inward ſenſation of things Intellectual and Divine, and are therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to whoſe Body and Soul, is added <hi>Mind or Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore then, to <hi>Love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind,</hi> is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to Adore and Delight in God, from a <hi>diſtinct perception,</hi> from an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſation</hi> as well of his abſolute Perfections in themſelves, as of His infinite Bounty and Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us. And thus I have explained the Terms, and ſtated the Nature of the duty in general.</p>
            <p>I proceed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as I propoſed, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, to conſider the particular parts, the neceſſary acts and exerciſes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:63466:45"/>of Love to God, Firſt, <hi>with all</hi> our Heart, and with all our Soul; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>with all our Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, the particular acts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the <hi>Love of God with all the Heart,</hi> and <hi>with all the Soul,</hi> are chiefly theſe,</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Preference of God to all other objects whatſoever. He that loves with Judgment, eſteems and values according to <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> according to the degrees of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and excellence in the object. As he readily acknowledges whatſoever worth or goodneſs he any where diſcerns, ſo he ſuffers not his Paſſion and deſire to go before his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>But God is a Being that exiſts of himſelf, in whom is implied what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can be ſuppoſed to be, and in whom all being is reſolved, as into its proper and moſt perfect cauſe. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſuppoſes impotence and controul, but Omnipotence implies the moſt abſolute perfection. Deſire of Good when known is <hi>neceſſary.</hi> But can
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:63466:46"/>any inſtance of goodneſs or perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be hid from his knowledge, or kept from his poſſeſſion, who is the cauſe of all things?</p>
            <p>Wherefore then, ſince all perfections are eſſential to this firſt and Original Good; one of the neceſſary acts of Love to ſuch a being is the preference of him to all other Beings whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. If our Love of God be with all the Soul, with judgment and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then we know that <hi>there is none in heaven but God, and none upon earth to be deſired in compariſon of Him;</hi> That he is the fountain of all the imperfect excellencies of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Beings; that he is the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and the moſt potent friend and benefactor; who made us by his Power, and ſuſtains us by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, guides us by his Council, aſſiſts us by his Spirit; pities our Weakneſs, pardons our Sins, and is ready, at laſt, to receive us into Glory. Whereſoever therefore, He is underſtood, all other objects, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and deſires, will neceſſarily fall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:63466:46"/>before him. For whatſoever beauty or goodneſs may be found in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther object, they are all derived from God, <hi>in whom all fullneſs dwells.</hi> That is the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Second particular implyed in the Love of God, <hi>with all the Heart,</hi> and <hi>with all the Soul;</hi> is a ſtedfaſt Faith in whatſoever he reveals. A ſincere affection is apt, in its nature, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get an unreaſonable credulity. It is very difficult to perſwade our ſelves that our friend, whoſe happineſs we know is our greateſt pleaſure, ſhould abuſe our Paſſion by deceit and guile, to ſport or private ends: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, notwithſtanding all the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of humane Nature, all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerities which may proceed from wicked diſpoſitions, and violent temptations; yet Love creates an intire and perfect confidence in one another. How much more if our Love of God be with all our Heart and Soul, ſhall we believe his Word, and rely upon his Promiſes? becauſe he is Truth it ſelf, and cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:63466:47"/>he is Wiſdom it ſelf, and cannot propoſe or promiſe at adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; he is Power it ſelf, and can bring into act whatſoever he decrees; He is Goodneſs it ſelf, and neither can, nor will deceive us. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Love of God be ſincere, and with underſtanding, the moſt intire and perfect confidence in his Word and Promiſes are neceſſary. We ſhall inquire into his Will, ſtudy his Laws, ſubmit our apprehenſions to his determinations, and ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatſoever he reveals. <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet, or a dreamer of dreams,</hi> Deut. 13.1, 2, 3. <hi>and giveth you a ſign or a wonder, and the ſign or wonder come to paſs, whereof he ſpake unto thee, ſaying, go after other gods which thou haſt not known, and ſerve them, thou ſhalt not hearken to that Prophet, or that dreamer of dreams, for the Lord thy God proveth thee to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your ſoul.</hi> The adhering firmly to the Word of God, though a Wonder
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:63466:47"/>ſhould be wrought in confirmation of a contrary doctrine, is made a teſt of our Love of God, by God himſelf. That is the Second.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Third particular implied in the <hi>Love of God, with all the heart, and with all the Soul,</hi> is ſuch an imitation of the Divine Perfections, as our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, and capacity will permit.</p>
            <p>Self-love, or a deſire of being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and perfect in the kind, is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary inclination, or the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of every being. And therefore whatſoever Good or excellence we clearly underſtand, as eſſential to, or perfective of our being, or conducible to the eaſe and convenience of our life, we cannot chuſe but deſire the poſſeſſion of it. It is not ſo properly an act of reaſon, as an inſtinct of nature. But if we <hi>love the Lord our God with all our Heart and Soul,</hi> with ſincerity and underſtanding, we ſhall diſcern the beauty, capacity, and perfection of our own nature, in the Qualities and the life of the firſt, and moſt perfect of rational Beings;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:63466:48"/>and ſhall therefore neceſſarily deſire to imitate thoſe Divine vertues which we ſo adore and love. The abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eſſence of God is impoſſible to be comprehended by a finite underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but we judge of the Divinity, as of all things elſe, by effects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, by his works of Creation and Providence, by his Univerſal righteouſneſs, wiſdom, purity, and goodneſs, ſo viſible in the government of the World. If we therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and admire theſe glorious Attributes of God, we ſhall endeavour to tranſcribe his Copy, and model our Souls according to this Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar; becauſe the reſolution of the mind, that ſuch a quality is worthy and excellent, includes deſire and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: we ſhall endeavour to be <hi>holy, as God is holy, in all our converſation, that as he is, ſo we may be in the World,</hi> wiſe in the management of our ends, juſt in our dealings, merciful to the diſtreſſed, ready to forgive our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in all things aſpiring after the Divine perfections, and ſetting the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:63466:48"/>Life of God before us, as the Rule of our Converſation: That's the Third.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth particular implied in the <hi>Love of God with all the Heart, and with all the Soul,</hi> is a conſtant uniform Obedience to his Will.</p>
            <p>What a chearful flexibility, what a readineſs to do any thing that may be grateful and pleaſant to each other, may be obſerved in the love of equals? If therefore love has ſuch a power, where the authority is precarious on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by conſent; how much more will the Love of God oblige us to the moſt diligent obſervance of <hi>His</hi> will, foraſmuch as the love of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors includes obedience in its nature. No man can intirely love a Prince, or a Father, that does not approve and obey his Precepts; and therefore St. <hi>John</hi> defines the Love of God by <hi>keeping his Commandments,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.3. This is the <hi>Love of God, that we keep his Commandments.</hi> We cannot add to infinite perfection, we cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige Him in any real ſervices, who is already Lord of all; there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:63466:49"/>therefore no poſſible teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Love to God, without the reſignation of our opinions, deſires, and actions to his will. This is all we have to offer: <hi>If a man Love me,</hi> (ſays our Saviour) <hi>he will keep my words:</hi> (Joh. 14.23.) and, <hi>he that hath my Commandments and doth them, he it is that loves me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would it not be the greateſt ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm in love, if our friend ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe us a method of happineſs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe his aſſiſtance, aſſure us of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and we ſhould receive it civilly, applaud his judgment, believe all he ſays, but never proceed to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the methods he propoſes? Hence thoſe who live in diſobedience to the Laws of God are ſaid to <hi>hate Him:</hi> Exod. 20.6.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if we have any true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of the Divine perfections, which love ſuppoſes, we know that God is infinite in wiſdom to direct and guide us; infinite in goodneſs, and will ſuit his commands to our abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; full of mercy and compaſſion,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:63466:49"/>and will pity our weakneſs, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our failings.</p>
            <p>If therefore love, whereſoever it is ſincere, is apt to create an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant deſire of pleaſing the object, even with the utmoſt hazard, and ſometimes by unlawful practices, by humouring vices, flattering deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſerving the baſeſt ends, any thing indeed that they think may gratifie the perſon. How much more will the love of God oblige us to the ſtricteſt care and obſervance of <hi>His</hi> will, becauſe we know that His will is perfect; He can command us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor can he be pleaſed with any thing, that is not truly Good. He cannot be giddy and inconſtant, frequiſh and uncertain, humorſome and hard to be pleaſed, as imperfect objects are; but He will receive our addreſſes, and accept our ſervices. He will enable us to obey him, and make the beſt conſtruction of all our ſincere endeavours, and at laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat our love in the everlaſting en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Himſelf. That's the 4th.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:63466:50"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt particular implyed in <hi>the Love of God with all the heart and with all the Soul,</hi> is the moſt hearty ſorrow whenſoever we ſhall offend him, with an earneſt deſire to be reconciled.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever loves, will endeavour to recommend himſelf, by an obliging deportment, to the good opinion of the object; purſues a kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, waits a ſutable return, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects at length the enjoyment of his hopes. If therefore he has given any juſt occaſion of Offence, by omitting what was neceſſary to be done, or by doing any thing that was contrary to his Pretenſions, or inconſiſtent with his Love, it muſt needs affect him with indignation againſt himſelf, that he ſhould bring his own ſincerity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to queſtion, injure the perſon, whoſe happineſs is his greateſt Joy, retard his progreſs towards that end he chiefly aims at, and ſuperinduce a Cloud upon that Sun, by whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence he lives.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo in reſpect of God, if we love him with Underſtanding, we
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:63466:50"/>cannot but purſue his favour, and moſt earneſtly deſire to be loved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; becauſe we know that our Love of God, if it be ſincere and pure, will be returned in the moſt ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing delights: we know that his Love is Life; that it is not an empty Paſſion, but exerted in the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial effects, and happy inſtances. And therefore that we ſhould have ſinned againſt him, muſt needs be the moſt inſupportable affliction; becauſe in proportion to the nature of our offence, our chief deſign of obtaining his favour, and the light of his countenance will be hindred; and all our work, of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, may be to begin again. And as we ſhall be deeply ſenſible of our offence, ſo ſhall we alſo be very ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous to be reconciled.</p>
            <p>One of the moſt eſſential acts of Love, is a deſire of the good opinion of the object; nor is any thing more directly contrary to that Paſſion, than ſtoutneſs and indifference. No man can ſit down and be ſatisfied
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:63466:51"/>under the diſpleaſure of his friend, till he has acknowledged his offence, dimulced his anger by ſutable medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, and all ſuch other acts, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his caſe, will ſuggeſt unto him.</p>
            <p>Thus as our Love of God will make us very careful to obtain and preſerve his favour, ſo ſhall we alſo be extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſolicitous, in caſe of offences, to be reconciled. If our love of God was ever real, it can never be withdrawn: when once we have underſtood, and have been warmed with the love of God, it is not poſſible, in the nature of the thing, that we ſhould ever be reduced to indifference; for the glory of God is immutable, and his Beauty perfect, which where they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, will of neceſſity both attract, and continue Deſire and Love, as being the only object that can fully delight and ſatisfie the faculty. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this all, but we know more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that we cannot be happy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Love: if He hide his face we are wretched and undone; that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Juſtice towards offenders, is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:63466:51"/>as certain an Attribute of God, as Infinite Goodneſs. Nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can diſcourage us, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give over our Confeſſions and Tears, our Vows and Reſolutions, and the tender of all ſuch ſatisfactions as are poſſible for us to make, till we have reaſon to hope, that our ſins are pardoned, and our perſons are again received into his favour.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the eſſential parts, the neceſſary acts of <hi>Love to God, viz.</hi> That we prefer Him to all other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects whatſoever, believe his Word, and rely upon his Promiſes, imitate his Life, and obey his Laws, be deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrowful whenſoever we offend him, and earneſtly endeavour to be reconciled. All theſe ſeveral expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are of the eſſence of Love, and flow from the nature of the thing.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed, as I propoſed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the ſecond place to conſider the more perfect exerciſes of Love to God, <hi>with all thy Mind. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:63466:52"/>
            <p>In the explication of the Words, it has been already noted, that the <hi>Love of God with all the ſoul, is ſuch an adoration of God,</hi> as proceeds from a ſenſe of the Glories and excellencies of His Being, as they are apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by reaſon, and inferr'd from his Definition, Nature and Operations; but the <hi>Love of God with all the mind,</hi> is with a more quick, and ſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Divine perfections, with reaſon improved into a more lively apprehenſion of the object.</p>
            <p>A young Philoſopher ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the benefits of <hi>frugality,</hi> ſuppoſe, or of any other Vertue, and ſhall be able himſelf to deduce the advantages of it, by the rules of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gic, and ſhall believe his deductions to be regular and true. But a man of Age and Experience, beſides what reaſon ſuggeſts, from cauſes to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, has a ſenſe and feeling of the thing, he is affected with it; it has ſeized and taken poſſeſſion of him, he is one with the Notion. Thus Reaſon infers the Perfections of God,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:63466:52"/>from neceſſary Principles, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſatisfied, and the Will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms ſuch acts, as are ſutable and conſonant to ſuch opinions and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Soul: But he whoſe knowledge has affected his mind, not only knows, believes, and acts accordingly; but he has alſo a more quick and ſenſible perception and enjoyment of the Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, by an inexplicable agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, harmony and delight; he is one with them, raviſhed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of Deſire and Love. And the particular acts implied in the Love of God with all the Mind are chiefly Three.</p>
            <p>The firſt is frequent Meditation,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and a due intention of the Mind, upon the beauty and excellencies of the object. This is both an act and a cauſe of the love of God with all the Mind. Where our affections are fixed, there all our faculties will be employed. Love therefore will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke us to the meditation of God, and Meditation will improve our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:63466:53"/>Knowledge and perfect our Love. For ſince it is impoſſible to diſcover a blemiſh in abſolute perfection, the more we pry into Him, the more of neceſſity, we ſhall love him. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever then is affected ſenſibly, and in his Mind, with the love of God, will ſeparate conſiderable portions of his time, for the contemplation of the Divine Perfections; He will abſtract his mind from ſenſible things, that it may be purer, and more free, more apt to apprehend, more eaſily impreſſed by objects Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Spiritual. Nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders our clearer Knowledge, and more ardent love of God, but the prepoſſeſſion of our affections, by the beauty and goodneſs of the World. Theſe we converſe with, theſe we admire and court; but as for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite perfections of God, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, as the Doctrine of the Church, and hope to enjoy them through the merits of Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tradition of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. We reſolve that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:63466:53"/>as indeed He is: and therefore we never endeavour to find out ſo much of his beauty, as by a due diſpoſition of Soul, without revelation or ecſtaſie, we might.</p>
            <p>Whereas if our lives were more retired, caſtigate and ſober, our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits would be purer, our minds more quick and vigorous, objects Divine and Spiritual would be more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, more eaſily felt, and enjoyed by us.</p>
            <p>It were eaſie to conſider particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and ſhow how a due intention of mind upon the attributes of God, will more ſenſibly affect us. Do we adore Him for ſo much of his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs, as appears at the firſt view, in the general, or towards our ſelves? How much more ſhould we be affected, if we look it round, and conſider throughly this perfection of the will of God? That God who is Omnipotent, and under no controle, ſhould be bounded in his Will, by the Laws of Goodneſs, Righteouſneſs
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:63466:54"/>and Mercy. That He ſhould vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to communicate his own likeneſs, and ſubject the whole Creation to the uſe and convenience of Man; that He ſhould love us when we were his enemies, and reſtore our corrupted nature to its firſt integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by the paſſion of his only Son. That He ſhould ſtill follow us with kindneſs, wait to be gracious, not eaſily provoked, longer before He puniſhes. That his love to Man ſhould be equal, and univerſal, but managed with the moſt perfect wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; diffuſed more warm, and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where it is neceſſary; withdrawn and eclips'd, as the temper of the ſubject may require it: and all this, without any cauſe, or motive from without himſelf, but it is the pure effort, and energy of his own nature, no ſudden paſſion to beget it, no ſlight, miſtaken injury, no pride or envy to withdraw it, but goodneſs, ſincere and pure, equal and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, exerted with the moſt perfect wiſdom towards the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:63466:54"/>from the beginning of the world, till time ſhall be no more. <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God!</hi> Theſe depths, and theſe riches of his goodneſs, are not to be underſtood, but by a due intention of the mind. But whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thus exerts his Mind, his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſelf, in the contemplation of God, will love Him with his Mind too, becauſe Deſire and Love are always equal to our knowledge. That is the Firſt.</p>
            <p>The Second particular implied in <hi>the Love of God with all our Mind,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is the Higheſt, and moſt extreme De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, in ſuch converſation with Him, and enjoyment of Him, as is ſutable to our preſent ſtate.</p>
            <p>Deſire of converſation with the object is a neceſſary act of Love. The nearer we approach it, the more we expect to be pleaſed; and when once we have attained to an intimate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, then all our previous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and deſire is perfected; We now enjoy the object in continual aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:63466:55"/>of mutual affection, we commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate our hopes and fears, our Joys and griefs, we conſult, adviſe, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt each other; and this indeed was the end at firſt propoſed. Thus alſo in reſpect of God, whereſoever the Glories of his nature are apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there the humble profeſſion of our Love, the deſire of his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the diſcovery of our needs, the opening of our hearts, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his aſſiſtance, the expreſſion of our paſſion in Hallelujahs, and Songs of Praiſe, will follow of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Where theſe are wanting, there can be no opinion of the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Omniſcience, of the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power of God.</p>
            <p>But if our love of God be with all the Mind, with a more quick ſenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe perfections, acts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will be our greateſt pleaſure, our moſt raviſhing Delight: For by theſe we converſe with that inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Majeſty, we adore, receive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns and pledges of his love, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of his favour, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:63466:55"/>in our choice. That's the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>The laſt particular act implied in <hi>the love of God with all the Mind,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is a fervent deſire of perfect union with Him, and the Everlaſting Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Him.</p>
            <p>Deſire of the moſt intimate uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (according as the object is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being enjoyed) is a neceſſary part of love. And in reſpect of God, there is no one thing that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do more plainly aſſert and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate, than the union of pious Men with God. Good men are ſaid to be <hi>joyned,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>glued to the Lord, and to be one ſpirit, to dwell in Christ, to put on Chriſt, to be as cloſely united as the Vine and branches, as husband and wife, as the foundation and the building, as the Soul and body.</hi> Finally, as <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>our bleſſed Saviour:</hi> for ſo our Saviour prays,
<note place="margin">Joh 17.21.</note> 
               <hi>that thoſe whom thou haſt given me may be One, as thou Father art in me, and I in Thee,</hi> that they alſo may be one in us.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:63466:56"/>
            <p>
               <hi>May be one in us</hi> not <hi>eſſentially,</hi> or hypoſtatically, but in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their will, in likeneſs of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, temper and deſign; as if they were acted by the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; and in this, the proper unity of Souls conſiſts. And thus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour explains the Unity of Believers with himſelf, by <hi>bringing forth the fruits of righteouſneſs, John</hi> 15.15.</p>
            <p>Indeed, the effects of this Union, the delights and pleaſures which fill the minds of thoſe who are thus united to God, are ineffable, and therefore, according to S. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 5.32. <hi>it is a great myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever therefore <hi>loves the Lord his God with all his mind,</hi> with clearer knowledge, and more pure deſire, will be impatient of a <hi>perfect <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> of the moſt full and ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fruition of God in Heaven. The more we know of God, the more our Souls will deſire him, becauſe he is abſolutly perfect, and therefore we are ſure to be for ever entertained with freſh diſcoveries
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:63466:56"/>of Beauty and Glory. Enjoyment will inflame our deſire, till our Souls ſhall be wholly reſolved into the object. O how deſpicable will all the World appear, even Liſe it ſelf, in compariſon of a more perfect participation of the Divine Nature! How earneſtly ſhall we expect, till our Knowledge ſhall be improved into its utmoſt capacity, <hi>that we may ſee him face to face!</hi> How ſhall we long for ſuch a compleat enjoyment as ſhall not be allayed by infirmities and ſins, by temptations and deſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, by natural corruptions and impure affections; but continue for ever, vigorous and fruitful, conſtant and indiſſoluble!</p>
            <p>And as theſe higher and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect degrees of Knowledge, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, ought to be purſued as a duty; ſo they are ſometimes beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diligent and ſincere, as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. God is pleaſed to <hi>manifeſt himſelf unto them, to raiſe</hi> their deſires, and refreſh them with returns of his
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:63466:57"/>Love, and <hi>cauſe them to drink of the rivers of His pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we never attain to this more ſpiritual frame; if our minds, through worldly impediments ſhall never be improved into a diſtinct and clear perception of the Attributes of God: Yet if our love of God be with competent knowledge, and great ſincerity, if it be fruitful in the neceſſary acts of Imitation, Faith, Obedience, and the reſt, it will be rewarded, and made perfect here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, though it never arrive at the more perfect Knowledge and Deſire of God here.</p>
            <p>And thus I have conſidered the particular parts, the neceſſary acts and exerciſes of love to God: Firſt, <hi>with all thy Heart and with all thy Soul,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>with all thy Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the duty ſo particularly ſtated and examined,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we may eaſily diſcern the reaſon of that primacy, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency, which our Saviour aſcribes to <hi>this</hi> above all the Commands of God, <hi>This is the firſt and great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:63466:57"/>And this was the Third head of diſcourſe propoſed.</p>
            <p>It is firſt in the diſpoſition of God himſelf.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> He begins his Inſtituion of Laws, with, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind.</hi> Deut. 6.5.</p>
            <p>It is firſt in the order of Nature,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it is the root, the principle, and reaſon of all other duties whatſoever.</p>
            <p>It is firſt in reſpect of the Object,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> end, or final reſolution of the Duty, being chiefly exerciſed upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is firſt in reſpect of Amplitude and Capacity,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> foraſmuch as all the other duties of Religion have a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary dependance upon it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to it.</p>
            <p>And the Duty being found ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable in its order,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſo pleaſant and agreeable to the humane Nature in it ſelf; my pains in propoſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, (which was the Fourth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) are, I hope, prevented.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:63466:58"/>
            <p>The diſtinct underſtanding of the Divine Perfections, requiring ſuch intention and purity of Mind, ſuch a concurrence of circumſtances, as are competent to very few, therefore our Saviour urges the duty of <hi>love to God</hi> by an Argument that falls under Senſe, and is eaſily underſtood of all, that is to ſay, our <hi>Relation to God, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though God is infinitely perfect, yet he vouchſaſed to impart his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and form a relation to himſelf, that he might exerciſe his Goodneſs upon us, and make us happy.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in our Creation, in the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Liberty, and Ingenuity of our Nature, acting as God <hi>freely,</hi> and for the ſake of ends, underſtanding clearly, loving regularly, capable of Arts, Philoſophy, Policy, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and are ſure to live for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in our Redemption; when we ſo fooliſhly deſire to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent; and did, what lay in us, to caſt off our Relation to God: then God, that knew our infirmities,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:63466:58"/>pitied our follies, and redeemed us, by the blood of his Son, from the captivity of ſin, from our miſerable ſervitude under the Tyranny of our ſelves, our irregular luſts and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and reſtored us to the rectitude of our Will, to the Love and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of himſelf again.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in His particular Care and Providence; The Government of God is managed by infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And though all his benefits are not beſtowed upon every man, yet, if we rightly judge, we ſhall find, they are diſpenſed with an equal and impartial hand. If one has riches, another has health; if one has exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal honour, another has a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; if one has ſtrength, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has wit: Every man for the moſt part, has ſome particular happineſs in his own condition, ſufficient to ballance his wants, <hi>Thou ſhalt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore love the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What therefore now remains,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> but that we reſolve to determine our
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:63466:59"/>Affections, which are never idle, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver indifferent, upon this moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Object; of whom our opinion ſhall never vary, our deſire ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cool, enjoyment never clog; where our reception ſhall be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and our paſſion encouraged; whoſe kindneſs is immutable, and whoſe Love is Operative: It is Strength in Difficulties, in Hazards Wiſdom, in Temptations Victory, in Diſtreſs a Refuge, in Fears a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, in Death everlaſting Life: to which of his Mercy may He bring us all, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake the Righteous: To whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all Honour, Praiſe and Obedience, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:63466:59"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. xxii. 39, 40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Second is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</p>
                  <p>On theſe Two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Phariſees envying the Fame of our Saviour's Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and fearing the ſucceſs of his doctrine, and the revolt of the Jews,
<note place="margin">V. 15.</note> 
               <hi>took counſel together how they might intangle him in his talk;</hi> and reſolved upon a Queſtion of State to be propos'd unto him; <hi>Is it lawful to pay tribute to Caeſar or not?</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 17.</note> To which they knew a direct and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive anſwer, would either betray him into the high dipleaſure of the King, or at leaſt into the hatred of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Faction of <hi>Herodians.</hi> But our Saviour, who knew their thoughts,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:63466:60"/>defeated their malice, by ſuch a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and inoffenſive anſwer, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Party could except againſt, <hi>viz. Render therefore unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,
<note place="margin">V. 22.</note> and unto God the things that are God's! and when they heard theſe words, they marvelled, and left him, and went their way;
<note place="margin">V. 23.</note> and the ſame day the Sadducees came to him alſo,</hi> who indeed believe no future ſtate at all, but they diſſembled their opinion for the preſent, and pretended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our Saviour, as if they ſincerely deſired his Judgment, in a caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Reſurrection of the dead, but, in truth, with intent to expoſe the doctrine it ſelf; Namely, <hi>if a Woman have ſeven Husbands upon Earth,
<note place="margin">V. 28.</note> in the Reſurrection whoſe of the ſeven ſhall ſhe be?</hi> In anſwer to which, our Saviour corrects their falſe and groſs opinion of the future life, and ſhows them their ignorance of the ſtate of the queſtion they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; <hi>For in the Reſurrection they neither marry,
<note place="margin">V. 30.</note> nor are given in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age;</hi> and thus with the ſame moſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:63466:60"/>perfect wiſdom, <hi>he aſtoniſhes the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,
<note place="margin">V. 33, 34.</note> and put the Sadducees to ſilence too.</hi> Laſt of all, a Lawyer having heard of the wiſdom of our Saviour, that he had put the Sadducees to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and was able to anſwer all the doubts and Queſtions concerning the life to come, inquires of our Saviour, under the ſtyle of <hi>Maſter,
<note place="margin">V. 36.</note> Which is the great Commandment? Jeſus ſaith unto him,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the Firſt and the Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> and the ſecond is like unto it,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf. On theſe two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words are a general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Way and Method, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may attain everlaſting life; of ſuch a converſation and courſe of action here, as will procure to us everlaſting bleſſedneſs in the World to come.</p>
            <p>And all the duties, qualities, and habits, which are required of us, as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:63466:61"/>conditions of Eternal life, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, by our Saviour, under theſe Two Heads:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The firſt reſpects our duty towards God; <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The ſecond reſpects our duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbour, in the words of my Text: <hi>And the ſecond is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf. On theſe two Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hang all the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of this uſeful and neceſſary Argument, I ſhall confine my Diſcourſe to this following Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſhall explain the nature of the duty, and conſider what is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by <hi>loving our Neighbour as our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I ſhall illuſtrate the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and neceſſity of univerſal love, and urge it upon your practice, by ſeveral Arguments, couch'd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in theſe words, <hi>Thy Neighbor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:63466:61"/>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I ſhall repreſent the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this command to the former, that of love to God, in ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; <hi>and the ſecond is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I ſhall conſider upon what Accounts the Law and the Prophets are ſaid to depend upon theſe two. <hi>On theſe two Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hang all the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly and Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I ſhall make Application of the Whole.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> the explication of the duty; what is underſtood by <hi>Loving our Neighbour as our ſelves?</hi> and that I may proceed more clearly, I ſhall briefly conſider theſe Three Things.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Who we are to underſtand by <hi>our Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What by <hi>Loving</hi> our <hi>Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> What by <hi>Loving our Neighbour as our ſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, by our <hi>Neighbour,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the object of the duty, we underſtand
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:63466:62"/>the whole Society of humane Kind, every Man that lives. Amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> indeed, this word was never underſtood to comprehend the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> but however it was uſed indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently for any <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> as in the Ninth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> and again, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſtand againſt the life of thy Neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 19.18.</note> that is, of any <hi>Jew,</hi> though not of any Man, for they hated the Gentiles, and eſteemed them accurſed.</p>
            <p>But under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, our Charity is inlarged to every individual Perſon, over the face of the whole Earth; and therefore our Saviour declares expreſly, that the <hi>good Samaritan</hi> was <hi>Neighbour</hi> to the <hi>Jew</hi> that was wounded, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.38. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> reciting this very paſſage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. changes the word <hi>Neighbour</hi> for that of <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> a word of the moſt indefinite ſignification of any that is uſed, <hi>He that loveth another hath fulfilled the Law,</hi> for all duties are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:63466:62"/>in this ſaying, namely,
<note place="margin">V. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> This for the object of the duty, our <hi>Neighbour, every man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed, as I propoſed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the ſecond place, to conſider the nature of the duty it ſelf; What it is, and when a Man may be ſaid to <hi>love his Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as all Mankind are made the object of our love, it would be abſurd to explain the nature of that love, by ſuch intimate acts of affection and deſire, as ariſe from a choſen friendſhip, or a near Relation; but our definition of <hi>univerſal Love</hi> ought to be very general, that it may be practicable in the utmoſt, and the true extent thereof, as a duty that reaches to the fartheſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Earth, and is exerciſed upon Perſons and Countreys we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw or heard of, as well as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe with whom we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
            <p>To love our <hi>Neighbour</hi> then, or the whole Society of Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:63466:63"/>whereſoever diſperſed and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered about the World, is, ſincerely and heartily to deſire and wiſh the happineſs of every Man; to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented and pleaſed that our Brethren ſhould ſhare with us, in all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and advantages we are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of enjoying; to promote our own particular good, with ſafety and regard to the intereſt of the whole: In a word, to <hi>Love</hi> our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> is to proſecute a publick intereſt, to conſent and aſſiſt, with all our hearts, in the mutual good of one another. That is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>I proceed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in the Third Place, to conſider what we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by <hi>Loving our Neighbour as our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>Love</hi> our Neighbour is the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; to love our Neighbour <hi>as</hi> our ſelves, is the Rule or meaſure in the practice of it, or the qualification with vvhich it ought to be exerciſed. And there cannot ſurely be a better, or a more eaſie copy propoſed to our
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:63466:63"/>Imitation. A Rule that is ſo ſtreight and perfect in it ſelf, and impoſſible to be miſtaken by us. Self-love is the firſt, and moſt evident principle of our being; every man underſtands and feels the nature of it, how ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and pure it is; how vigorous and ſtrong, how conſtant and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable. But thus are we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by our Saviour, to love our Neighbour, even <hi>as our ſelves;</hi> with the ſame moſt ardent deſires, with the ſame ſincere endeavours, to divert impendent evils, and procure all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible good to others, as we would do to our ſelves. This in general.</p>
            <p>More particularly I ſhall conſider the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as thy ſelf,</hi> in a double ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as obliging us to an intire and perfect Love; that we have a regard to all our Neighbours inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; that we love him in the ſame <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>latitude</hi> that we love our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as obliging us to love him after the ſame <hi>manner</hi> that we love
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:63466:64"/>our ſelves; to purſue his good with the ſame affections and diſpoſitions of mind, that we find in our ſelves, in the proſecution of our own.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to Love our Neighbour as our ſelves, implies a perfect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire affection to all his ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts; that we love him in the ſame extent and latitude that we love our ſelves.</p>
            <p>All our poſſibilities of happineſs are contain'd and comprehended in theſe four particulars, viz. <hi>our Soul, our Life, our Eſtate and Reputation.</hi> Every man has a tender reſpect for theſe; it is the buſineſs of our Lives, and the object of our Reaſon, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as happy in all theſe ſeveral ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, as we can; no man chuſes folly or iniquity, diſgrace or poverty, diſeaſes or death, ſimply, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>proper notion</hi> of them; but, according to our meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the opinion that we have of things, we endeavour to avoid them as <hi>evil,</hi> and procure the good that is contrary thereunto. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:63466:64"/>then <hi>to love our Neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> according to this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words, is to deſire his good, as we do our own, in all his ſeveral capacities; to be really plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his happineſs in any of his intereſts, and ready to aſſiſt him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our power.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the intereſt of his Soul;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> a man of univerſal Charity, envyes no mans parts or Vertue; but is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the Image of God whereſoever he diſcerns it, with the rays of Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs which are ſcattered amongſt men. He is troubled for the wickedneſs of the wicked, paſſionately ſenſible of the horrid conſequences of their proceedings; <hi>his eyes,</hi> with <hi>David, run down with tears, becauſe men keep not the Law of God.</hi> He is ready to communicate his Knowledge, to give his Counſel, to inſtruct the ignorant, to recal the erring, to reprove the fooliſh, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays of himſelf, <hi>Not ſeeking
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:63466:65"/>his own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>love</hi> our Neighbour <hi>as our ſelves,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> implies a regard to his Life, his Eſtate and Property. A man of univerſal Charity is not only juſt to all men,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 4.6</note> 
               <hi>not defrauding or oppreſſing his Neighbour in any matter.</hi> Neither is he <hi>indifferent</hi> only to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours intereſt, doing no unhandſom thing to any man, but he poſitively <hi>ſeeks</hi> and <hi>ſtudies</hi> his Neighbours weal. He rejoyceth at any opportunity of doing kindneſſes to men, he receives and addreſſes the complaints of the Oppreſſed, viſits the Sick, cloaths the Naked, feeds the Hungry, he is <hi>ready to diſtribute,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> and is given to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality.</hi> According to S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Charitable man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. (to which we ſhall have a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſpect, in our preſent diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.) <hi>v.</hi> 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Charity ſeeks not his own,</hi> is not circumſcribed within the narrow compaſs of his own advantage; is not frozen into dry ſterility, but fruitful and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:63466:65"/>in acts of Mercy and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. He conſiders himſelf, as a member of the one Society of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature; and therefore, as a partner with all the World, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes a publick intereſt, is glad of the proſperity of thoſe above him, obliging, by all the arts of Civility, and handſome converſation, to thoſe on a level with him, ready to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the weak, and aſſiſt the needy.</p>
            <p>And as he is kind to all, ſo he is not eaſily provoked into diſpleaſure againſt any man. He is not quick and forward to diſcern the injuries and ingratitude of brutiſh people; he is not apt to aggravate, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a fault; he is ready to believe that it proceeded of miſtake, of raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or inadvertency, rather than of malice or evil will. For ſo ſays the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 4. Love is of a gentle, eaſie diſpoſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, hopeth all things, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently in a flame or feaver, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents an injury with a calm and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:63466:66"/>ſteddy mind, and ſtudies no revenge; for <hi>Charity will cover the multitude of ſins.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10 12. Pet. 4.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>To love our Neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> implies a regard to his Fame and Reputation. <hi>A good name is better than life it ſelf,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon.</hi> We prefer it to all other intereſts whatſoever, by the inſtincts of our very Nature. No man can endure to be repreſented ill, becauſe it is the parent of contempt and neglect, which of all other things is the moſt abhorr'd. And therefore a man of univerſal Charity, will be tender of his Neighbours Credit. He hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſhes that all men would behave themſelves as they ought to do, and live with decency, and honour in the World. <hi>Charity rejoyceth not in the wickedneſs of the wicked, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in the truth,</hi> that is, in the upright converſation of men; ſo <hi>Grotius</hi> upon the place.</p>
            <p>He is more ready to diſcern the vertues and excellencies of others,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:63466:66"/>than his own. He chearfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges worth, and allows ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient praiſe whereſoever it is due. He puts the beſt interpretation upon any action that the nature of the thing will bear. He judgeth no man till he underſtands the courſe of his Converſation, nor any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular action, till he knows the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and affections of it. (<hi>Affectus tuus imponit nomen operi tuo,</hi> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks <hi>de offic.</hi>) He follows the rule of <hi>Epictetus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Ench.</note> 
               <hi>does any man drink much wine? ſay not that he drinks to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch, but, ſimply, that he uſes to drink much;</hi> becauſe the ſame action may proceed from a good, as well as from an evil cauſe. <hi>He that ſtrikes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> (as <hi>Simplicius</hi> in his Expoſition of the place) <hi>may do him good, and he that feeds him may be his enemy: He that ſteals, as the caſe may be, may do no ill, and he that relieves another may do unjuſtly.</hi> And therefore a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable man is ever ſlow, and ſparing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:63466:67"/>of his cenſures, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he hopeth all things,</hi> and is willing <hi>to believe the beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Ears are ſhut to idle tales, and evil reflections upon any man; or if he is forced to hear them, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſtifle the report, and clear the imputation, that, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, it may ſtop with him. He is troubled for ſo much of it as he finds to be true; <hi>and with an angry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, he drives away the back biters tongue</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>as the North wind driveth away rain.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25.23</note> And thus <hi>by covering a tranſgreſſion he ſeeketh love, Prov.</hi> 17.9.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of all theſe inſtances of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Charity; a man that is really a friend to all, will be courteous and eaſie, gentle and civil in his outward converſation and deportment.</p>
            <p>Haughtineſs, or elation of mind, proceeds from an <hi>undue account,</hi> a diſtinct unreaſonable opinion of our ſelves above our Neighbours. And
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:63466:67"/>all moroſe and ſupercilious converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are the effects of conceitedneſs and pride, of diſcontent and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that we are not valued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the price we have ſet upon our ſelves. But a man that is frank and ingenuous, <hi>that loves his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as himſelf,</hi> treats and uſes every man with the chearfulneſs and civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a friend. His own deſires and expectations from his betters, are the meaſure of his deportment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe below him.</p>
            <p>He then that <hi>loves his Neighbour as himſelf,</hi> will be eaſie of acceſs, courteous and ſincere in ſpeech, civil and obliging in all his converſation with him. Since he is a friend to all, he will not ruffle, provoke, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any man; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Charity is benign, yielding and complaiſant, knows no <hi>ſupercilium,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is not full of himſelf,
<note place="margin">V. 4.</note> 
               <hi>he is not puffed up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is, <hi>to love our Neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> as we underſtand it of loving him in all the ſeveral inſtances
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:63466:68"/>wherein we love our ſelves; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended chiefly under his Soul, his Life, his Eſtate and Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the Duty, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> not only obliges us to have a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all his intereſts, but to love him <hi>alſo after the ſame manner,</hi> that we love our ſelves; to purſue his good, with the ſame affections, and diſpoſitions of mind, which we find in our ſelves in the proſecution of our own.</p>
            <p>It is always to be ſuppoſed that the Rule or Exemplar is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than the Copy. The love of a Man to himſelf is ſo unmixt and pure, the unity ſo perfect, that it is not poſſible he ſhould confer it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another in the ſame degree, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he could really and naturally u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite him to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thus God Almighty is propoſed to us, the moſt imperfect of rational Beings, as the Pattern of our Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:63466:68"/>
               <hi>Be ye Holy as God is Holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.24.</note> ſays St. <hi>Peter: Be ye perfect as your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father is perfect,</hi> St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> But in theſe, and ſeveral other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we muſt not underſtand the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as denoting an <hi>exact I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentity,</hi> but only that our Principle be <hi>ſincere,</hi> our vertue <hi>true,</hi> though far inferiour in degree.</p>
            <p>Wherefore in our preſent caſe, the qualification of the duty, <hi>as thy ſelf,</hi> though it may not import an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of love, which is impoſſible; yet, at leaſt, it ſignifies that we love our Neighbour with the ſame kind of affections, and diſpoſitions of mind, with which we love our ſelves: and therefore <hi>Eraſmus</hi> expounds the words by <hi>perinde ac teipſum, in like manner as thou lovest thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> With the greateſt Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Senſe; every Man is affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted intimately with his own affairs, he feels every motion that concerns them, becauſe he knows he muſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:63466:69"/>enjoy, or endure the event of his deſigns. And thus we are enjoyn'd to love our Neighbour, <hi>as our ſelves;</hi> Not only to do him no hurt in any intereſt, neither yet to do him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice only; but to be inwardly <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> and <hi>affected</hi> with his caſe; that we be Men of <hi>Bowels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.22.</note> apt to be wrought into pity, compaſſion, and deſire to do him good, into Joy and delight at any proſperous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We love and purſue our own particular happineſs with ſolicitude and diligence. Our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible apprehenſion, and innate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of good, provoke and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage our moſt earneſt endeavours, (according to our knowledge) to promote it. No Man is indifferent and cold in his own purſuits. We think no pains too great, we leave no ſtone unturn'd, we grudge no preſent ſelf-denial, in the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our own deſigns. Thus alſo <hi>thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour even
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:63466:69"/>as thy ſelf,</hi> with fervency of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, with a Zeal for his Good. It is not a tender expreſſion, a friendly wiſh, an unwilling word, a cold eſſay, that fulfils the duty; but a chearful ſervice, ready moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, effectual aſſiſtances: that we be patient to hear, and willing to underſtand and be concern'd, in a caſe that is worthy of us: that we lay it to our heart, and put it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, according to diſcretion, by our counſel, our friend, our perſon, our purſe, as the occaſion may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, for thus we love our ſelves <hi>with paſſion and ſolicitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, With conſtancy,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and everlaſting affection. Self-love can never abate or cool; every Man purſues what he thinks to be good, to the laſt: it is a natural principle, an eſſential property of our Being, which can never be extinguiſhed. But thus are we obliged to love our Neighbour, even <hi>as our ſelves,</hi> all the days of our life. This duty of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:63466:70"/>univerſal love is never perfected. It is not enough that we have been uſeful and beneficial in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſtance: but we muſt never ſtop, never contract our ſelves, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver imagine that we have paid this debt of univerſal Charity; but ſo long as we have ability and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, ſo long as we have objects before us, that is, ſo long as we live, we muſt dilate and expatiate our ſelves to the benefit of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for <hi>Thou ſhalt love him as thy ſelf;</hi> as well in all the ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances wherein thou loveſt thy ſelf, as with the ſame affections and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of thy mind; with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and paſſion, with fervency and Zeal, with ſteddineſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p>And thus, as briefly as I could, I have explained the duty of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Love; and by comparing the temper of our Souls, and the courſe of our converſation, with the rules and meaſures I have now laid down, we may know infallibly, whether we
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:63466:70"/>are endowed with this grace of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or no; whether <hi>we love our neighbour as our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are we pleaſed with the practice of Vertue, or any worthy quality, whereſoever we diſcern it? or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are not the infirmities, nay, the debaucheries of Men, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and ſport?</p>
            <p>Do we govern our deſires and aimes by the rules of equity and love? Do we uſe no tricks, no mines, no unhandſome arts, to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent another?</p>
            <p>Are we content that every Man ſhould proſper and be happy? Are we ready for every good work? <hi>Do the Loins of the poor bleſs us,
<note place="margin">Job 31.20.</note> are they warmed with the fleeces of our wool?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 31.20.22.22.</note> Do we govern our Authority over inferiour Men with Juſtice? <hi>Do we not trouble our own fleſh?</hi> Prov. 11.17. <hi>Do we not rob the poor, becauſe he is poor, and oppreſs the afflicted in the gate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May it not be ſaid of us, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> complains, (Eccleſ. 4.1.) <hi>On
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:63466:71"/>the ſide of the oppreſſor there was po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, but the oppreſſed had no Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are we willing to diſcern, and praiſe the vertues of our Neighbour, and to hide his faults?</p>
            <p>Can we chearfully hear the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of another, and not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe the Character by ſome malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inſinuation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does not our Soul deſire evil,
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.10.</note> and does our neighbour find any favour in our eyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are we civil and ingenuous in our Carriage towards all? Are we meek and approachable, ſincere and plain, gentle and eaſie to be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p>Are we never weary of well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never diſcouraged by our own miſtakes in objects, by the tricks and deceits that may, ſometimes, be put upon us, by the ingratitude of thoſe we have obliged; or the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe from whom we had expectation; by the errours that a Zealous Charity may run into, or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:63466:71"/>the cenſures of unworthy Men, to which it may ſometimes be expoſed? Do we centre in a ſenſe of Duty, and the ſincerity of our principle and deſign, reſolving never to look back or faint, but perſevere in a ſteddy courſe of univerſal Charity to the end? This is <hi>to love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed, as I propoſed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the ſecond place, to perſwade you to the practice of this duty of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity, by certain motives and encouragements, couched and implied in theſe words, <hi>Thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are obliged to proſecute a publick intereſt, to be kind and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate to all, becauſe we are <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;</hi> and that <hi>implies,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, The Neceſſity of the thing:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>To love our neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> is our real Intereſt, becauſe of our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation and neceſſary converſe with one another.</p>
            <p>No affection or property of humane nature is more evident, than a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Society.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:63466:72"/>
            <p>Our innate impreſſes of natural Affection, Goodneſs and Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; our paſſions of Deſire and Love, our abilities of inventing uſeful Art, our faculty of Speech, which is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Man, and what only ſerves the purpoſes of Society, do all ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it: and the impotence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability of man, in a looſe and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſtate, to perfect his capacities, to ſatisfie his natural deſires, nay, to ſupport and defend his life, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it.</p>
            <p>But without an hearty conſent in the mutual good of one another, without policy and a publick intereſt, Society would be dangerous and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, black and uncomfortable ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude our only refuge, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Reaſon, without Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is miſchievous ſubtlety, and would prove the greateſt inſtrument of evil in the World. The fierceneſs of the Leopard, and the ſtrength of the Lyon, would not be ſo dreadful as the underſtanding of Rational Nature devoid of Juſtice. Every
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:63466:72"/>man would be againſt his Brother, our life would be a ſtate of war, a continual hoſtility. Here an attempt by force, there by ſubtlety and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvention, every where diſtruſt and fears, guards and preparations of defence.</p>
            <p>So that according to the Principles of our Nature, and the deſign of our Being, we are one Society, one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, one common happineſs is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us all.</p>
            <p>And no man that ſeparates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Community, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth with himſelf, to ſtand on his own legs, and acquire whatſoever pleaſes him, by <hi>any means,</hi> without reſpect to others, can ever proſper or be ſafe; becauſe he can never hope to be endured. Every man has a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſpect for his Life, his Honour, and his Intereſt, which, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they are forcibly invaded, will provoke him to retaliate the injury. No man can expect with reaſon, to be treated more civilly himſelf, than he treats his neighbour. Such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:63466:73"/>is Vanity, there is no foundation for ſuch a deference in Nature: but he raiſes the whole Society againſt himſelf; and how he ſhould acquit himſelf in ſuch an unequal combat, is not eaſie to imagine. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Qui ſe amat, hunc, &amp; alios ſic amare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6. <hi>Lipſ. in Loc.</hi>
               </note> (ſays <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>nec ſibi ſed toti genitum ſe credere mundo. He that loves himſelf will love his neighbour, and conſider himſelf as born for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the World. He that hates his brother,</hi> ſays S. <hi>John,</hi> (1 Ep. 2.11.) <hi>walks in darkneſs, but he that loves his brother abideth in the light.</hi> The Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor of <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſs,</hi> ſignifies the knowledge, or ignorance, of our intereſt: the ſelfiſh man is as wretched as thoſe who are blind, or travel in the dark, expoſed to grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous evils, dangerous precipices, ſharp and rugged ways, <hi>But he that loveth his brother abideth in the light;</hi> acts wiſely, proceeds with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and good ſucceſs, lives ſafely and ſecurely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is no danger of his <hi>ſtumbling,</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:63466:73"/>of his <hi>offending others,</hi> or being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second motive to univerſal Love and Charity,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> couch'd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in theſe words, <hi>thy Neighbour,</hi> is the propriety in, and the relation that we have to one another. He is <hi>thy Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Mankind are of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and original; ſons of the ſame God. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no patre conditi, unâ matre tanquam fratres uterini editi,</hi> as the Father ſpeaks (S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) ſtamped with the ſame Divine Image, equally inſpirited with the breath of God. The meaneſt man in the world agrees with him that is the greateſt, in that that is truly Great and Noble in him, his Reaſon and Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then, ſince we are all children of the ſame Family, and, which is more, profeſſors of the ſame moſt holy Faith, <hi>Citizens with the Saints, of the houſhold of Faith,</hi> (Eph. 2.19.) Nay <hi>farther,</hi> ſince our union
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:63466:74"/>is more intimate, and we are <hi>members one of another,</hi> (Eph. 4.25.) we ought <hi>to love as brethren;</hi> to ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize as parts of the ſame body, to be eaſily touch'd with a ſenſe of each others evils, foraſmuch as the caſe of our Neighbour is, in a moral ſenſe, our own; and we are ſtupid, if we neglect it. There is ſomething of our ſelves in every man; the ſame Divine Principle inlivens us, the ſame blood runs in all our veins: We have therefore a propriety, a <hi>real in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in one another. So that to <hi>love thy Neighbour</hi> is indeed <hi>to love thy ſelf.</hi> That is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> From the neceſſity of a publick ſpirit in order to our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and from the Relation that we ſtand in to our Neighbour, ariſes another motive to univerſal Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, namely, the beauty, the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the pleaſure of the thing. Whatſoever actions neceſſarily tend to the good of man, and are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Laws and impreſſions of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:63466:74"/>humane Nature, muſt of neceſſity be full of eaſe and pleaſure. The Soul exults, and enjoys her ſelf, in the practice of them, as her <hi>proper</hi> acts and <hi>operations.</hi> As, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, an irrational courſe of proceeding is unnatural, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a violence to our frame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, as poyſon or the ſharpeſt pains are to the body.</p>
            <p>But to love our Neighbour as our ſelves, is not ſo properly a rational act, a thing that is fit to be done, as, <hi>Reaſon it ſelf,</hi> our eſſential dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, <hi>our very form.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To purſue the ſatisfaction of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turai deſires by <hi>ſtrength,</hi> by <hi>craft,</hi> or by any means, is the property of Beings meerly ſenſitive. But there is no other notion of humane Nature, than that of <hi>making a diſtinction of actions;</hi> nor of Rational Ends, but <hi>Good;</hi> nor of Good, but <hi>publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> And therefore univerſal Love, or a regard to others, as well as to our ſelves, is the perfection of our Being. For let our diſtinctions,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:63466:75"/>otherwiſe, be never ſo many, or ſo great, yet if our <hi>Will by nature,</hi> be <hi>unbounded,</hi> there is no <hi>Eſſential</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between us and Brutes. Hence <hi>Love,</hi> according to St. <hi>John,</hi> is the very definition of <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is the ſtandard of Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perfection: 1 Joh. 4.8. <hi>Beloved, Let us love one another, for God is Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How eaſie then would all Men be in this their moſt Divine and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate? What a confidence would Love create, what delight, what truſt, what aſſurance, what a free and chearful intercourſe? No Man would be diffident of his Neighbour, as averſe to his intereſt, or croſs him as an enemy; but we ſhould enjoy the unvaluable bleſſings of ſociety with eaſe and peace.</p>
            <p>But a Man of a ſhrivell'd, narrow ſpirit, that is wholly reſolved into himſelf, proceeds againſt univerſal Law and Right; Rows againſt the ſtream, with difficulty and fear, with perplexity and danger: he cannot
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:63466:75"/>live alone, and yet he can never be ſure of the good will of thoſe with whom he muſt converſe: he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways practiſing hypocriſie, and muſt accompliſh himſelf with arts of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, and tricks of deceit, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcern'd, which is impoſſible, he may deceive the World. He is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a perpetual conſtraint in the management of his converſation, for fear he ſhould be betrayed into that ſhame, confuſion and hazard, which attend the detection of baſe deſigns, and which they deſerve, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from this Royal Law, of <hi>Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> a Law which in the practice of it would put a new face upon the World, would baniſh gnawing cares and angry fears, and give ſincerity and chearfulneſs to every countenance. There could be no miſery amongſt Men. We ſhould all be happy in one another, and anticipate that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, harmony, and love, which are ſuppoſed to conſtitute the joys of Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:63466:76"/>
            <p>And thus I have explain'd the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of univerſal Love, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the beauty and neceſſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from the words, <hi>Thy Neighbour. Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It now remains that I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the likeneſs of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to the former, that of Love to God, <hi>and the ſecond is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the nature of the duty, they both oblige us to the ſame <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In extent and ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; they are both comprehenſive duties, the former containing all the ſeverals of the firſt, the latter of the ſecond Table.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In that they ſuppoſe, and are predicated of each other. <hi>He that loveth God will love his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.20. As <hi>Philo</hi> truly ſays of moral vertues in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, they <hi>follow</hi> and are <hi>linked</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:63466:76"/>
            <p>As alſo, Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, both the conſtruction, and the reaſon of this expreſſion, <hi>On theſe two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, They conſent and agree with theſe. St. <hi>Paul</hi> interprets the word by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Rom. 13.9. <hi>If there be any other Commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this ſaying,</hi> namely, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> This is the end, the ſcope, and the deſign of the Law and the Prophets. All the Precepts of the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion have their ground and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence in theſe two, and into theſe they are finally reſolved; out of theſe univerſals, flow all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of both Religions.</p>
            <p>And therefore for a Concluſion of the whole, I ſhall only pray to God,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> that he would affect our minds with a ſenſe of his goodneſs to us, who has given us a Religion ſo eaſie to be learn'd and underſtood.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:63466:77"/>
            <p>If we heartily believe the Being of a God, we cannot but deſire his favour; and to ſuch as theſe, no bleſſing can be compared with a clear revelation, without diſtinct and certain knowledge of our duty; becauſe we then are free from anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fears, and doubts about the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Religion; We aim at a ſteddy end, without the mazes, and uncertain wandrings of Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We run within the lines, the ground is ſet out, and the Goal is before our eyes. Our whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention may be taken up in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing our minds with the love of God and Man; the rode to happineſs is plain and eaſie. <hi>This is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And O! that we could be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to lay aſide all falſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Religion; and believe our Saviour, and accept him upon his own conditions: that we would purſue the favour of God and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs in the way of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:63466:77"/>univerſal Charity. For, believe it, no Faith, no Creed, no Church-Communion, no outward Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, no external Piety, without the <hi>Love of God, and Man,</hi> will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail us any thing in the Day of Judgment; No, though we ſhould be honoured with the power of working Miracles; and ſhould caſt out Devils in the Name of <hi>Christ,</hi> yet unleſs we cloath the Naked, viſit the Sick, aſſiſt whom we may, and pity all, we ſhall ſurely be ſhut out, with, <hi>Depart from me, I know ye not:</hi> Matt. 7. ult.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore be perſwaded, ſince ſo much depends upon it, to ſet our ſelves induſtriouſly upon the practice of theſe Duties, that we may procure to our ſelves univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal love and peace; the good will of God and Man in this preſent life, and everlaſting Glory in the World to come.</p>
            <p>To which, God of his mercy
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:63466:78"/>bring us all, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake the Righteous, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt be all Honour, Glory, Praiſe, and Love, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:63466:78"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. xii. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Be not overcome of evil, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evil with good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO gratifie the preſent paſſion or deſire by fraud, by force, or by any means whatſoever, without reſpect to right or wrong, to good or evil, is the eſſential diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of irrational brutal Nature. But to look before us, to act for the ſake of ends; to do, or to forbear, as the event and conſequence of the thing ſhall appear to be good or evil to us; is the diſtinction, the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, indeed, the definition of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able creatures. But becauſe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable faculty in man (who is the moſt imperfect in the kind) is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcur'd and prejudic'd, by the unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:63466:79"/>union of the Soul and Body, in our preſent ſtate; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, who is Wiſdom it ſelf, has at ſeveral times, but at laſt, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by his Son, in that moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect inſtitution of Reaſon, as well as of Religion, contain'd in his holy Goſpel, aſſiſted our weakneſs, clear'd our notions; drawn out and ſet on work thoſe eternal principles of Truth and Goodneſs, which may be undiſcern'd, but can never be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from our own minds.</p>
            <p>And amongſt all the excellent rules of Wiſdom and Practice therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, there is none of ſo high, ſo exalted a nature as the love of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for this alone is propoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtyle and character of <hi>Divine Perfection. Be ye therefore perfect as your father which is in heaven is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> A Precept which, through the prejudice of our paſſion, and the depth of its reaſon, is not eaſily underſtood, hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, more hardly practiſed; yet
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:63466:79"/>in truth it is every way our intereſt, as well as an indiſpenſable duty, <hi>and therefore if thine enemy hunger,
<note place="margin">V. 20,</note> feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink, for in ſo doing thou ſhalt heap coals of fire upon his head. Be not overcome of evil,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> but overcome evil with good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Judaizing Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>Meg. Eccleſ. Hiſ. Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> and the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> had extremely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the Chriſtian Religion, by aſſerting the obligation of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law, the lawfulneſs of a diſſembled Apoſtaſie, and a liberty of indulging any Luſt or Vice we ſhall be addicted to. Now to hinder the ſpreading of theſe pernicious Doctrines, and to aſſert the Truth and Purity of the Chriſtian Religion, againſt thoſe falſe and ſpurious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, which they had given of it, S. <hi>Paul</hi> inſinuates, is his chief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in this his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, Ch.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>And Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> he ſhews that the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law was but a type or
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:63466:80"/>ſhadow of a more perfect inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, which in after time ſhould be eſtabliſhed: <hi>Ch.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>That that time is now accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and the Ceremonial Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed; and that therefore we are now obliged to thoſe more perfect and ſubſtantial duties, which were ſignified and repreſented under the Types and Figures of the Law: <hi>Ch.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Finally,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That Chriſtianity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the reformation of our lives, in rectifying the evil diſpoſitions of our Souls, in conforming our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, deſires, and actions, to the moſt pure and perfect Laws there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as the uſe of the whole Diſcourſe, <hi>I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the mercies of God,</hi> Ch. 12.1. <hi>That ye preſent your bodies,</hi> all your bodily corrupt affections and deſires, a <hi>Living Sacrifice,</hi> a whole
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:63466:80"/>burnt-offering to God; That ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely reſign your ſelves, and ſuffer your Religion to have its laſt deſign and end upon you:
<note place="margin">V. 2.</note> 
               <hi>And be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to this World,</hi> (for ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle proceeds to particulars) <hi>But be ye transform'd by the renewing of your minds;</hi> with fervent Piety and Devotion towards God, <hi>V.</hi> 11. with ſincere and univerſal Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, extending even to the love of Enemies, in the words of my Text, <hi>For if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Be not overcome of evil, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome evil with good.</hi> Theſe words are a Precept of univerſal obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which concerns our behaviour, under injuries received, <hi>Be not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of evil; and our deportment to wards thoſe</hi> who injure us: <hi>but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evil with good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we are inſtructed how to behave our ſelves under injuries received, <hi>Be not overcome of evil.</hi> We
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:63466:81"/>are not obliged to a Stoical inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; To deſtroy our Paſſions is no perfection, but a debility, and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the mind: but to command them, to keep them within their bounds, to exerciſe them upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Objects, and to a juſt degree, is the honour of a Man, and the duty of a Chriſtian. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it ſelf, <hi>Be not overcome of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> ſuppoſes, and allows a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the injury, but obliges us to govern our reſentments by the rules of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; to mold our ſpirits into a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of meekneſs; kindneſs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion; that we may be then moſt pleaſant to our ſelves, when we ſtand in the greateſt need of counſel and advice; that no provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation may be able to diſcompoſe our minds, or tranſport us into fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh, indecent words, or actions, much leſs into meditations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge: But that we receive the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury with Patience, conſider it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dately, conſtrue it fairly, excuſe it
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:63466:81"/>ingenuouſly, or if the malice be too plain to be hid, then to refer the Judgment of your cauſe to God: <hi>Be not overcome of evil. But over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evil with good.</hi> In the former clauſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Be not overcome of evil,</hi> is underſtood of the injury re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; but evil in the latter clauſe, <hi>overcome evil with good,</hi> has reſpect to the injurious perſon. Conquer your enemy by kindneſs; bring him to confeſſion of his baſeneſs, to repentance, to offers of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, to the very ſame ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even from his heart, which you would propoſe to your ſelf to force him to, if you could conquer, and diſarm him in the open Field. <hi>If thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink, for in ſo doing thou ſhalt heap coals of fire upon his head; be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi> And thus much for the Explication of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the ſenſe of the words: By which we may ſee, that it has no
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:63466:82"/>relation at all to Government, or the puniſhment of Offenders againſt the peace of the publick; Nor to the reſentments of Princes, or the Wars and Peace of Nations. Nor laſtly, to the defence of our Perſons, our lives and fortunes, againſt the aſſaults and out-rages of wicked men. Theſe are Conſiderations of another nature, with which our preſent argument is not in the leaſt concern'd. But the Duty of the Text concerns the moderation of our Paſſions, under any opprobrious words, or ill deſigns, which have been ſpoke, or form'd againſt us: and obliges us to forbear revenge; to ſeek no private, illegal ſatisfaction for any ſuch injury received; that we do not therefore become his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, becauſe he ſeems to be ours; that we harbour no ill will, ill wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or ill deſigns againſt him, but endeavour to reconcile him to a ſtate of amity and friendſhip, by a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to oblige and ſerve him. <hi>Be
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:63466:82"/>not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the clearer illuſtration of this moſt perfect Precept of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I ſhall briefly conſider theſe Four Things.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>The indiſpenſible Obligation of the Duty, by the expreſs Command of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>The fitneſs and neceſſity of the thing conſidered in it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>The rewards and benefits, which will accompany the practice of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, and Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>The poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of performing it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt of all, This Duty,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>That we be not overcome of evil, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evil with good,</hi> is indiſpenſably required.</p>
            <p>It is not to be underſtood as a Council of perfection, as a glorious
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:63466:83"/>unattainable temper, which we are not obliged to purſue; but it is a poſitive Duty, an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, in which we are no more at liberty, than in any other precept of our Religion. S. <hi>Paul</hi> deſignedly in this, and the following Chapters, collects and repeats the principal duties of Chriſtianity,
<note place="margin">V. 2.</note> or <hi>what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.</hi> And amongſt the reſt he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the <hi>love of enemies:</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 20.</note> and upon this he inſiſts and ſtays for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Verſes, as being a duty more unwillingly received, and inforces at laſt, in the words of my Text, <hi>Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi> And our Saviour himſelf, in the 5. of S. <hi>Matth.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and urges, the <hi>love of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> after the ſame manner, and under the ſame form, as he does the reſt of his precepts, without any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation or indulgence whatſoever, <hi>v.</hi> 44. <hi>But I ſay unto you, love your enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:63466:83"/>
            <p>Indeed there is no one duty of our Religion more ſtrictly enjoined, more frequently inculcated, or preſs'd by a greater variety of cogent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than that before us.</p>
            <p>The very Spirit of Chriſtianity is meekneſs, and mutual condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<note place="margin">Col. 3.8.</note> and therefore we are obliged to put away all <hi>anger, wrath and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; to ſuffer all things, to be kind,
<note place="margin">Jam. 1.19</note> to think no evil:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.5</note> to be patient towards all men, to render to no man evil for evil, or railing for railing,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3 9</note> but contrariwiſe bleſſing. To put on as the elect of God,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.12</note> bowels of mercy, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind; meekneſs, long-ſuffering, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.31</note> forgiving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven us.</hi> And all this is inforced upon us, by the terrible ſanction of God's everlaſting anger towards us: <hi>For if ye forgive not men their treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, neither will your heavenly father forgive you,</hi> S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.15.
<q>
                  <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Chryſoſtom, is more
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:63466:84"/>odious to God, than a man that is thirſty of revenge;
<note place="margin">Hom. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Geneſ.</note> the miſchief of this ſin is ſuch, that it deprives a man of the benefit of God's mercy, and will not ſuffer it to have any place upon him.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we ſee, that to reſtrain our Paſſion, to be meek in Spirit, ſlow of reſentment, dead to revenge, eaſie to forgive, and ready to oblige an enemy, is an indiſpenſable duty of our Religion.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, that our Saviour ſeems to <hi>curſe</hi> the Cities of <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum, Chorazin,</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they withſtood his doctrine, S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>Wo unto you Chorazin, wo unto Bethſaida, and thou Capernaum, which art exalted unto heaven, ſhalt be brought down to hell.</hi> Or that S. <hi>Paul</hi> curſed <hi>Alexander</hi> upon a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal injury offer'd to himſelf, in his Second Epiſtle to <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>the Lord reward him according to his works.</hi> Or that the moſt holy Saints have taken a liberty of imprecating evil upon their enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. <hi>They
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:63466:84"/>compaſſed me about with words of hatred, they rewarded me evil for good, and hatred for my good will: let his days be few, and let another take his office: let his children be fatherleſs, and his wife a widow; let his children be vagabonds and beg their bread, let the extortioner conſume all that he has: as he loved curſing, ſo let it come upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the practice, I ſay, of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and of thoſe holy Saints, ſeem contrary to the precepts of <hi>love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you.</hi> S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>'s reſolution of that queſtion is ſufficient, <q>who obſerves how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it is in Scripture, to foretel the event of future evils, under the form of an imprecation. So that all ſuch places as I have now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, are to be underſtood, not as the wiſhes of the ſpeaker, but as Prophecies of what will certainly come upon them. And as for that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> He obſerves that he ſays
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:63466:85"/>not <hi>reddat,</hi> let the Lord, but <hi>reddet dominus,</hi>
               </q> the Lord will reward him for it. There is therefore no indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to be found, no diſpenſation allowed; it is poſitively required, <hi>That we be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> if it be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>there is nothing more fit and reaſonable in it ſelf;</hi> and this was the ſecond head of diſcourſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>As the benefits of cohabitation and Society are great, ſo has it alſo this inevitable inconvenience, that amongſt ſo many perſons, of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent humors, diverſe intereſts, and various deſigns; Juſtice and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty will be violated, private and open injuries will be offered; there are always ſome that will be ready to build their reputation, or fortune, upon the ruine of other men. Even common Converſation cannot be ſo
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:63466:85"/>cautiouſly maintain'd, ſo diſcreetly manag'd, but diſguſts and piques will often happen. It is impoſſible then but offences will come. The Air will as ſoon be fixed, and the Sea reduced to reſt; as humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ſhould be altogether free from occaſions of offence. Either therefore we muſt learn this leſſon of meekneſs, and mutual condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or prepare our ſelves for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſtate of war.</p>
            <p>If we can neither hide our reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prudently, nor bear them pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, we may lay aſide all hope of living peaceably in the World. Our whole life will be ſpent in vindicating our real, or ſuppoſed injuries one upon another. Every man would be againſt his Neighbour, till, in time, that kind would be deſtroyed. So that if we were not obliged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain our Paſſion, and paſs over in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries by the Laws of our Religion; the very neceſſities of our Nature and Being, would direct us to it. And
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:63466:86"/>therefore, <hi>a wiſe man,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, deferreth his anger, it is his glory to paſs over a tranſgreſſion,</hi> Prov. 19.11.</p>
            <p>Indeed Revenge is the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable thing in the World. It is contrary to all the principles of Juſtice and equity, that any man (where it may poſſibly be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) ſhould be Party, Witneſs, Judge, and Executioner in his own Cauſe. Every man is partial to himſelf; and we are then moſt weak and unfit to judge, when we are ruffled and provoked: that little ſtock of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that we are maſters of, is apt to be overborn by the Violence of Paſſion. Even <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf, though he might dart his favourable rays of his own accord, yet he could not ſend out his Thunderbolts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent and Counſel of the gods. Indeed, the imperfection of the humane nature is ſuch, that it is not fit to be truſted with a liberty of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging injuries</hi> at diſcretion. Such a power can never be proper, never
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:63466:86"/>ſafe, but in the hands of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe vengeance is, and to whom it belongs to repay:</hi> Who is infinite in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and cannot be miſtaken in a circumſtance; who is infinitely juſt and good, and therefore loves and pities the offender. That is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as the return of good for evil is indiſpenſibly required,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as it is fit and reaſonable in it ſelf, ſo ſhall it alſo be rewarded with Victory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> And this was the third Head of Diſcourſe propoſed.</p>
            <p>The very Command it ſelf, <hi>That we overcome evil with good,</hi> is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable ſecurity to us, that by returning good for evil, we ſhall ſurely conquer, and ſubdue the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer.</p>
            <p>So that the reward of meekneſs, or a patient ſuffering of injuries, is not only that general peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and tranquillity of mind, which accompany the practice of all
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:63466:87"/>Vertue, and which will eſpecially ariſe from the ſubmiſſion of our will to God, in this moſt difficult in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo contrary to our own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt deſires: nor is it onely that great reward in Heaven, which our Saviour has promiſed to thoſe who patiently bear reproach, St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. <hi>which changes the injury into a Crown,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 16. <hi>ad</hi> 1 Cor. 6.</note> and makes us like to God,</hi> as St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> obſerves.</p>
            <p>But the benefit of Patience, and the Reward of returning good for evil, is preſent and more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate; all that is deſigned or hoped for by revenge, will more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and far more effectually be obtained, by meekneſs and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>What is it that we propoſe to our ſelves by revenge? Is it the Vindication of our honour, that we may teach the Aggreſſor how much he was miſtaken in his Man? that we may be known hereafter to be Men of ſpirit? and procure to our
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:63466:87"/>ſelves reſpect, or fear at leaſt? or, is it the reparation of the Injury ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained; and the prevention of the like attempts hereafter, by return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a greater load of evil upon the injurer, than he had brought on us? Why, both theſe ends of honour and ſatisfaction, will be more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly attained by courteſie and kindneſs, than by deep reſentments and revenge.</p>
            <p>For ſuppoſe you have ſucceſs, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you ſubdue your enemy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, afflict him, bring him on his knees; yet if the account be fairly adjuſted, you will find your ſelf as far from any real ſatisfaction now, as you was before; becauſe it coſt you more than it was worth. <hi>You ſay,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>de Ira, Lib.</hi> 1.</note> you cannot bear an injury; it is falſe: He that can bear anger, can bear an injury.</hi> There cannot be a greater torment to one's ſelf, than a thirſt of Revenge. What tumult and confuſion does it raiſe in our minds? what horrid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:63466:88"/>what impatience of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, what a perfect diſcontent, till our end be accompliſht? How is a Man unmann'd, and forſaken of himſelf, that is under the power of this unreaſonable paſſion? How do the thoughts of the Perſon diſorder him? How is he ſtruck at the ſight of him? his Eyes diſtorted, his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage changed, his Joynts infeebled, as if he were acted by an evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? <hi>He that nouriſhes a deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom</hi> 41. <hi>in Act. Apoſt.</hi>
               </note> ſays St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, carries a Lictor always about him, to ſcourge and laſh him, a glowing fire to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, that will never ſuffer his Soul to rest.</hi> So true is that of St. <hi>Ambroſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Offic. Li.</hi> 1.</note> Vincitur ab inimico qui ſe vindicat, non vincit.</hi> He is ſubdued and conquered, that revenges him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon his adverſary. So that, upon the matter, there is no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial ſatisfaction to be hoped for by revenge; Nor indeed any <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Eſteem, or true Reputation to be gained thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:63466:88"/>
            <p>All that we propoſe by Revenge, is to approve our ſelves to be Men of tenderneſs and reſolution, that we expect to be uſed with caution and civility; that we are no vile, or abject perſons, no proper ſubjects of deriſion and contempt: and this, it may be, you may make good.</p>
            <p>But, did not the Violence of your Paſſion, did not your Reſentment, with all your practice upon it, <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour</hi> and expoſe you more, than the Conqueſt of your Enemy could do you Credit?</p>
            <p>Is any thing ſo contemptible as a Man in paſſion? St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (as well as <hi>Seneca</hi>) compares him to a mad Man. <hi>The ſymptoms,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of madneſs and anger are the ſame: a bold and threatning countenance, reſtleſs and involuntary motions, change of colour, deep and frequent ſighs are the ſigns of madneſs; and Heat of blood, Redneſs of face, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Lips, gnaſhing Teeth, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Joynts, abrupt and ſtammering
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:63466:89"/>Speech,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. de Irâ L.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 1.</note> with an horrid ugly Viſage, are the ſymptoms and effects of anger.</hi> And therefore he concludes, <hi>that it is hard to ſay, whether anger be a Vice more detestable, or more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore, whilſt a Man aſſerts his courage, he expoſes his Wiſdom, it may eaſily be reſolved, what right, upon the matter, he has done to his honour.</p>
            <p>But after all, the ſucceſs is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the deſign may be detected, the Revenge prevented, the enemy more inſolent, injuries repeated, and your Honour more expoſed: ſo that the ſtudy of Revenge is very uncertain in the event; or if it ſucceeds, the ſatisfaction that it brings, is as dear, as it is imperfect.</p>
            <p>But by meekneſs, bearing patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and returning <hi>good</hi> for <hi>evil,</hi> we ſhall attain our ends upon our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, more eaſily, more certainly, and with better reputation. For Patience under an injury received,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:63466:89"/>leſſens the evil of it to ones ſelf. The evil of an injury conſiſts in our ſenſe, and apprehenſion of it; but if we are not affected by it, it loſes its edge and force upon us. Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment certainly inflames, but never cures the Wound: it aggravates the pain, and afflicts us more than the injury it ſelf. <hi>If we ſit down with patience,</hi> ſays <hi>Tertullian, We are not hurt; and if we are not hurt, there is then no occaſion of Revenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, as patience prevents the evil of an injury to ones ſelf, ſo is it alſo a great and a real revenge upon our enemy: His deſign is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe and vex us, to irritate and provoke us; but if we contemn and ſlight his eſſays, his end is fruſtrated, and he is the greateſt ſufferer, in that he cannot <hi>move</hi> us.
<note place="margin">Son.</note> 
               <hi>The Anvil ſuffers nothing by the heavy blows that are laid upon it, but the hand of him that ſtrikes is benum'd and ſtrain'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:63466:90"/>
            <p>This then is certainly the nobleſt, as well as the ſtricteſt ſatisfaction we can take; this is the ſureſt proof that we are men of honour. To bluſter and be dreadful, is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or commendation in any Being; perfect motions are eaſie and familiar, but whirlwinds and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes are therefore dreadful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are unnatural. Steddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, immobility, not to be affected by any thing without it ſelf, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of perfection. The higher and more perfect Regions are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed, free from tumults, clouds and tempeſts. They are the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Regions, that are affected by every vapour.</p>
            <p>He then is the brave and gallant Man, that deſpiſes an injury, and ſcorns to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to an affront. <hi>Quem injuria non incurvat.</hi> But to ſtudy Revenge, is to complain and ſink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a wound: it is at the beſt, but a refuge of ſhame, and the ſanctuary of a doubtful reputation. Nor is it
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:63466:90"/>honourable only in it ſelf, ſtrictly and rationally conſidered; but our enemy ſhall underſtand it ſo; He ſhall as really ſubmit himſelf, be as effectually ſubdued, by the return of good for evil, as if we had intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubjected him by force: for ſo ſays the Apoſtle in the Verſe before my Text; <hi>if thine enemy hunger,
<note place="margin">V. 20.</note> feed him; if he thirſt give him drink: for in ſo doing, thou ſhalt heap coals of fire upon his head.</hi> By ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected kindneſs, we ſhall work upon him, mollifie and melt him into Repentance, ſubmiſſion, and deſires of an everlaſting friendſhip. By Revenge a quarrel is prolonged; but Patience, and the return of good for evil, are apt to work upon the rougheſt temper. The ſweetneſs and gentleneſs of the humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are loſt and hid, for a time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a cloud of Paſſion and Anger; but by yielding to it, by giving room, we ſhall diſſipate the vapour, and the man will return to himſelf again.</p>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:63466:91"/>
            <p>And thus it appears that the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Meekneſs, Patience, and forgiving Injuries, how difficult ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may ſeem to perſons under the prejudice of falſe opinions, and the power of evil habits, is never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs our intereſt and our honour, as well as an indiſpenſable duty: ſo true is that of <hi>Solomon, He that is ſlow to anger,
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.29.16.32.</note> is of great underſtanding.</hi> And again, <hi>He that is ſlow to wrath is better than the mighty; and he that rules his ſpirit, than he that takes a City.</hi> That is the Third.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>And if to overcome our enemy by kindneſs be commanded of God, if it be reaſonable in it ſelf, if it be truly great and noble;</hi> if it be rewarded with Victory and Honour, it cannot be doubted, but, Fourthly and Laſtly, it is poſſible to be performed.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, our mind is under great diſadvantages in our preſent ſtate, and therefore we can never hope to
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:63466:91"/>attain the perfection of any Vertue; but we are as free in reſpect of our iraſcible paſſions, as we are in the reſt: We are no more driven or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated in this, than in any other of the powers and faculties of our Souls; and therefore undoubtedly we may reſtrain this paſſion, in a good degree, if we are not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſelves. Our paſſions are ſubject naturally, by the deſign and order of our frame; and therefore it cannot be ſo difficult, as it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, to oblige them to their proper places. They are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of our Underſtandings, and although it is impoſſible, indeed unneceſſary, to deſtroy them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Paſſions and our Reaſon, though they are really diſtinct, yet they are never to be ſeparated. To reſolve of an object that it is evil, and to deteſt and hate it, are acts of the mind, form'd, of neceſſity, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Yet if we be careful we may maintain the precedency and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:63466:92"/>authority of our reaſon, for in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts that Dominion over our ſelves, our choice, and actions, which give us the denomination of reaſonable creatures.</p>
            <p>The truth of it is, we are apt to indulge and nouriſh this Paſſion of Anger, we are willing to believe that it becomes us to be tender and ſenſible, fierce and implacable; to ſlight the moſt valuable thing, even Life it ſelf, and ſacrifice it to a <hi>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio</hi> of miſtaken Honour. And now that we have cheriſhed this Paſſion for many years, exerciſed our ſelves continually in it, yielded to all the extravagancies of it; now we hope to excuſe our ſelves, by pleading the impoſſibility of reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. Difficult indeed we have made it to our ſelves, but the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is ſuperinduced and adventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; and therefore ſtill, if we would take the pains to maſter our Spirit, as perhaps we have done to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:63466:92"/>elate and exalt it, we may be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in a good degree. <hi>Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca,</hi> upon the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>will paſs over all impediments.</hi> No affections of the mind are ſo fierce and obſtinate,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen. de Ira, Lib.</hi> 1.</note> ſo much them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but they may be tamed by Diſcipline. Reaſon duly exerciſed, will conquer any paſſion. In our preſent caſe, Let a Man but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, till his mind be affected with the evil, and unreaſonableneſs of Revenge, and he will be quickly able to forbear it.</p>
            <p>Let him that is tempted to anger, ſay, (it is St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s advice.) <hi>What can I do to you,
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Hom. in John. c.</hi> 1.</note> both my tongue and my hands are tied up by another;</hi> and this would be matter of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, a temper to them both.</p>
            <p>Let him meditate on his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, and abate a little, of that too high opinion, which perhaps he may have of himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:63466:93"/>
            <p>Let him remember how unguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his own behaviour many time may be; how much he may ſtand in need of forgiveneſs himſelf.</p>
            <p>Let him conſider, that no Man is invincible, that he may meet with thoſe that are as obſtinate and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as himſelf. And when once theſe cauſes, namely, Pride, Self-will, and Humour are removed, we ſhall return of courſe to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Goodneſs of the humane nature: a great many injuries will vaniſh into nothing; Great ones will appear indifferent, and the greateſt may be eaſily ſupported.</p>
            <p>Finally, Let us ſet before us the Examples of great and holy Men, who when their enemies have been under their power, when they might have taken their utmoſt revenge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, have paſs'd over all their injuries and affronts with neglect
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:63466:93"/>and pity. And thus we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our ſelves by the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſucceſs of others, as well as by the reaſon of the thing. Time would fail me to tell of <hi>Joſeph, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Job,</hi> the <hi>Publican,</hi> St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and the reſt, whoſe ſtories are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Holy Scripture; it is enough,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> that <hi>we look unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſed the ſhame; and prayed for thoſe who inſulted over him, and ſlew him, Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do. If you ſay,</hi> ſays Saint <hi>Auguſtine, How ſhall I ever hope to do as our Lord has done? Conſider where he did it, on the Croſs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>T.</hi> 10. 2da. <hi>fer. in Rog. Serm.</hi> 1.</note> where he acted alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as a man, and propoſed himſelf to our imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, I hope, upon the ſtrength of ſo many conſiderable Motives, we may be all perſwaded, at leaſt, to attempt the maſtery of
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:63466:94"/>our ſelves. The end is ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and the means ſo reaſonable and likely to attain it, that our beſt endeavours will be both juſtified, and rewarded. It may be difficult at firſt, to change a habit, that is riveted by long indulgence; but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacity and time will overcome it. Nature delights and haſtens to throw off all obſtructions; and when once we have made a little way, we ſhall then proceed, <hi>ſecundo flumine,</hi> and be over-joyed at the recovery of our primitive, our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the ready aſſiſtances of God, who will facilitate our diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, aſſiſt us by his Wiſdom, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us by his Power, and refreſh us by the irradiations of his Love, till the Victory be obtained: and we, at laſt, triumph in that moſt Perfect and Eternal ſtate of Bliſs, which is prepared for thoſe, <hi>who by patient continuance in well doing,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> ſeek for Glory and Immortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:63466:94"/>
            <p>To which, of his mercy, may he bring us all, for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, the Righteous; To whom, with the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all Honour, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Praiſe, Dominion and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, now and for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Amen.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:95"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63466:95"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>W. Kettilby.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Sermon preached before the King at <hi>Windſor, June</hi> 13. 1680. on <hi>Matt.</hi> xvi. 26.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preach'd before the Lord Mayor, <hi>Feb.</hi> 5. 1681. on <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 165.</item>
               <item>The Liberty of Humane Nature diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd, ſtated and limited; in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached before the King and Queen at <hi>Whitehal. Jan.</hi> 19. 1689. on <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>All four by the Rev.</hi> Mr. J. Lamb.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hesketh</hi>'s ſerious exhortation to frequent Communion. <hi>Octav.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—'s Caſe of Eating and Drinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily. <hi>Oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—'s Piety the beſt Rule of Orthodoxy.</item>
               <item>Religion the Perfection of Man. <hi>Oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pattern of pure &amp; undefiled Religion.</item>
               <item>Expoſition on the Church Catechiſm.</item>
               <item>The Faith and practice of a Church of <hi>England</hi> man. Edit. 3.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation Book, MDCVI. concerning the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God's Catholick Church, and the Kingd. of the whole world.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
